<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An alarme to awake church-sleepers. Describing the causes, discovering the dangers, prescribing remedies for this drowsie disease.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 190 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 89 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08263</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A826A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R119</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">64550765</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 64550765</idno>
            <idno type="VID">184293</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08263)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 184293)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2857:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An alarme to awake church-sleepers. Describing the causes, discovering the dangers, prescribing remedies for this drowsie disease.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 160 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Matthew Symmons in Gold-Smiths Alleyan Red-Crosse Street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published, perused &amp; amended for the benefit of all those that are either infected herewith or in danger so to bee."</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Includes errata: p. 12.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages are stained and tightly bound with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sleep --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church attendance --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sleep substances --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:184293:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184293:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184293:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184293:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>AN</hi> ALARME TO AWAKE Church-Sleepers.</p>
            <p>Deſcribing the Cauſes, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering the Dangers, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing Remedies for this Drowſie Diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſped, peruſed, &amp; amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for the benefit of all thoſe that are either infected herewith, or in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſo to bee.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MATH. 26.40.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>What, could yee not watch with mee one houre?</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON: Printed for <hi>Matthew Symmons</hi> in <hi>Gold-ſmiths Alley</hi> in <hi>Red-croſſe-ſtreet.</hi> 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:184293:3"/>
            <head>To the carefull and conſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable hearer of Gods Word, comfort in the meditation of theſe Scriptures.</head>
            <p>BLeſſed is the man that heareth me,<note place="margin">Prov. 8.34</note> watching daily at my gates watching at the poſts of my doores,</p>
            <p>The eare that heareth the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe of life abideth among the wiſe.<note place="margin">Prov. 16.31</note>
            </p>
            <p>To him will I looke that is poore,<note place="margin">Eſa. 66.2.</note> and of a contrite heart, and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth at my Word.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed are your eyes,<note place="margin">Matth. 13.16.</note> for they ſee; and your eares for they heare.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto you that heare,<note place="margin">Mar. 4.24.</note> ſhall more be given.</p>
            <p>Verily,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.24.</note> verily, I ſay unto you, He that heareth my Word, and beleev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on him that ſent mee, hath
<pb facs="tcp:184293:3"/>everlaſting life, and ſhall not come into condemnation, but is paſſed from death to life.</p>
            <p>He that is of God,<note place="margin">Joh. 8.47</note> heareth Gods Word.</p>
            <p>My ſheepe heare my voyce,<note place="margin">Jo. 10.27.</note> and I know them, and they follow me.</p>
            <p>Faith commeth by hearing,<note place="margin">Ro. 10.17</note> and hearing by the Word of God.</p>
            <p>Receive with meekneſſe the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted Word,<note place="margin">Iam. 1.21</note> which is able to ſave your ſoules.</p>
            <p>Who ſo looketh into the perfect law of liberty,<note place="margin">Iam. 1.25.</note> and continueth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, he being not a for getfull hearer, but a doer of the worke, this man ſhall be bleſſed in his deede.</p>
            <p>As new-borne Babes deſire the ſincere milke of the Word,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.2.</note> that yee may grow thereby.</p>
            <p>Behold, I ſtand at the doore,<note place="margin">Rev. 3.20.</note> and knocke. If any man heare my voyce, and open the doore, I will come in to him, and ſup with him, and he with me.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:184293:4"/>
            <head>To the drowſie ſluggard, watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, upon the peruſall of theſe Scriptures.</head>
            <p>B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t my people would not hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken unto my voyce:<note place="margin">Pſal 81.11</note> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> would none of me.</p>
            <p>So I gave them up unto their owne hearts luſt, <note place="margin">12.</note> and they walked in ther owne counſels.</p>
            <p>Becauſe I have called,<note place="margin">Pro 1 24, 25, 26, 27, 28.</note> and yee have refuſed, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I alſo will laugh at your cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>How long wilt thou ſleepe,<note place="margin">Prov. 6.9.</note> O ſluggard? when wilt thou ariſe out of thy ſleepe?</p>
            <p>This is a rebellious people,<note place="margin">Iſa. 30.9.</note> lying children, children that will not heare the Law of the Lord.</p>
            <p>What meanest thou,<note place="margin">Ionah 1.6.</note> O ſleeper.</p>
            <p>This peoples heart is waxed groſſe,<note place="margin">Mat. 13 15</note> and their eares are dull of hearing, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>He that rejecteth me,<note place="margin">Ioh. 12.48</note> and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not my words, hath one that judgeth him; the word that I have
<pb facs="tcp:184293:4"/>ſpoken, the ſame ſhall judge him in the laſt day.</p>
            <p>And there ſate in a window a certaine young man, named <hi>Euty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 10.9.</note> being fallen into a deep ſleepe, and as <hi>Paul</hi> was long preaching, he ſunke downe with ſleepe, and fell downe from the third loft, and was taken up dead.</p>
            <p>Awake thou that ſleepeſt,<note place="margin">Eph. 5.14.</note> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe from the dead, and Chriſt ſhall give thee light.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>To the careleſſe hearer, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring eares.</head>
            <p>Keepe thy foot when thou goest to the houſe of God,<note place="margin">Eccl. 5.1.</note> and bee more ready to heare, then to give the ſacrifice of fooles.</p>
            <p>Watch and pray,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.41</note> that yee enter not into temptation.</p>
            <p>Take heed, what you heare.<note place="margin">Mar. 4 24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Not the hearers of the Law,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.13</note> are juſt before God, but the doers of the Law ſhall be juſtified.</p>
            <p>To day if you will heare his voyce harden not your hearts.<note place="margin">Heb. 3.7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Be ye doers of the word,<note place="margin">Jam. 1.22.</note> and not hearers onely, deceiving your owne ſoules.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:184293:5"/>
            <head>A Table of the ſeverall Chapters of this Treatiſe, and matters contained therein.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>The Contents of the <hi>1.</hi> Chap.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SLeepe properly taken,</hi> what it is, pag. 1. Whence it commeth. 2. the Authour thereof, <hi>ibid.</hi> How needfull it is, 3 4. <hi>Ordinary</hi> when lawfull, 5. when unlawfull, 6. <hi>Extrordinary</hi> occaſions through meanes, naturall, 7. ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, 8. <hi>Sleepe figuratively taken,</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>godly,</hi> 9, 10. in reſpect of the <hi>ungodly,</hi> and that as well for <hi>ſinne,</hi> (conſidered both in <hi>generall,</hi> 11. (where divers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblances are ſet down, between <hi>ſleepe</hi> and <hi>ſinne,</hi> 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18.) and in <hi>particular,</hi> 19.) as the <hi>effects</hi> of ſinne, 20. in reſpect of the <hi>godly</hi> and <hi>ungodly</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184293:5"/>joyntly conſidered, 21. wherein the death of the <hi>godly</hi> and <hi>ungodly</hi> agree, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26. wherein they differ, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31. <hi>Sleepe</hi> how taken in this Treatiſe, 32.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>The Contents of the <hi>2.</hi> Chapter.</head>
               <p>Eight Reaſons ſhewing and proving the utility and neceſſity of this Treatiſe, 33, 34, 35, 36, 37, 38, 39, 40, 41, 42.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>The Contents of the <hi>3.</hi> Chap.</head>
               <p>The cauſes of Church-ſleeping, <hi>from Satan,</hi> who bringeth the ſame to paſſe ſixe ſeverall wayes, 43, 44, 45. <hi>from our ſelves,</hi> through floathfulneſſe, 46 care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe 47. intemperancie, <hi>ibid.</hi> and 48. hatred of the Preacher, 49. diſ-eſteeme of the Word read or preached, 49, 50 Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence unto the admonitions and reproofes of the Word, 51. ſhameleſneſſe, <hi>ibid.</hi> inconſiderate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, 52. want of Gods feare, 53.
<pb facs="tcp:184293:6"/>cuſtome and willingneſſe, 54. <hi>From others,</hi> both <hi>Preachers,</hi> in ſundry particulars, 55. and <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> both through commiſſion, 56, and omiſſion 57.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>The Contents of the <hi>4.</hi> Chap.</head>
               <p>Arguments againſt Church-ſleeping, <hi>from God,</hi> in five partic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulars, 59, 60, 61, 62. <hi>from the Word</hi> in reſpect of its dignity di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly evidenced, 63, 64, 65, 66. neceſſity 67. utility, 68, 69, 70, 71, 72. <hi>from the Preacher</hi> in five particulars, 73 <hi>from the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation</hi> in two particulars, <hi>ibid.</hi> and 74. from <hi>the place of meeting</hi> in foure particulars, <hi>ibid.</hi> and 75. from <hi>the end of comming,</hi> 76. from <hi>the time</hi> in fixe particulars, 77. from <hi>Satan</hi> in foure particulars, 78, 79 80. from <hi>our ſelves</hi> in nine particulars, <hi>ibid.</hi> and 81, 82, 83, 84. from <hi>ſleepe, ibid</hi> from <hi>ſleepers</hi> in ten particulars, 85, 86, 87.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>The Contents of the <hi>5.</hi> Chap.</head>
               <p>Objections for Church-ſleeping
<pb facs="tcp:184293:6"/>anſwered, being taken from <hi>the ſinne it ſelfe,</hi> as that it's no great ſinne, 88, 89, 90. it's ordinary and uſuall, 91, 92. it's not hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to others, 93. it's not ſo bad as ſome others committed at Church by them that are awake, <hi>ibid.</hi> it's not done of ſet purpoſe, 94. it's there but a napping, 95. from <hi>the perſons committing it,</hi> ſuch as are accuſtomed hereunto, 95 are old and weake, 96. watch on the other dayes of the weeke, and labour hardly, 97, 98. roſe that day very early, 99. have far to Church, ſit far from the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, &amp;c. 100. thinke they may get up at another time, or at home, what they then loſe, 101, 102. of the precifeſt ſort, 103. from <hi>the Preacher,</hi> alledged to be no Scholar, 104 105, 106. to live ſcandalouſly, 107. to have done his Neighbour wrong, <hi>ibid.</hi> to continue long in his Sermons, 108. from <hi>the matter delivered,</hi> alledged to bee not worth the
<pb facs="tcp:184293:7"/>hearing, 109, 110. the ſame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore inſiſted upon, 111, 112. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vective, 113, 114. frequently of hell and damnation, 115, 116. erroneous and hereticall, 117. that wherewith his hearers are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready acquainted, 118 unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and not tending to edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 119. from <hi>the perſons repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it,</hi> ſuch as have little to doe, 120. ſuch as are herein moſt faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>The Contents of the <hi>6.</hi> Chap.</head>
               <p>To avoid Church-ſleeping, wee muſt, <hi>before wee come to Church,</hi> take notice of gods goodneſſe in affording his Word, 122. conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for what cauſe, and to what end we goe to Church, <hi>ibid.</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve our naturall conſtitution, 123. labour for a true hatred and deteſtation of this ſin, 124. hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger after the Word, 125. (where wee have the meanes preſcribed wherby to attain hereunto, 126) reſolve to attend unto the Word, and make conſcience therof, 127.
<pb facs="tcp:184293:7"/>uſe the creatures ſparingly, 128. conſider whither we are a going, &amp;c. 129. pray for the Preacher, our ſelves, and the Word, <hi>ibid.</hi> An objection anſwered, 130. <hi>When we come to Church,</hi> we muſt, <hi>in generall,</hi> take heed to our affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, 131. get our eyes anointed with eye-ſalve, and our eares o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, <hi>ibid.</hi> bee poſſeſſed with Gods feare, 132, 133. be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the benefit we may get by the Word read or preached, 134. call to minde that there will bee ſtore of witneſſes to riſe up againſt us, if we ſhall thus ſinne, 135. <hi>In particular,</hi> in hearing wee muſt uſe attention, 136. intention, 137. retention, 138. devotion, <hi>ibid.</hi> ſubjection, <hi>ibid.</hi> diſcretion, 139. meanes to performe thoſe in five particulars, 139, 140, 141. <hi>After we are come from Church,</hi> we muſt uſe examination, 142. meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, 143. repetition. <hi>ibid.</hi> confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, 144. practiſe, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:184293:8"/>
               <head>The Contents of the <hi>7.</hi> Chap.</head>
               <p>The application of the fore-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcourſe for <hi>reprehenſion,</hi> and that both of <hi>Preacher</hi> in two par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, 145. and <hi>people</hi> in ſeven particulars, 146, 147, 148, 149, 150, 151, 152. for <hi>exhortation</hi> unto Preachers, 153, 154. unto people, 155, 156, 157, 158, 159, 160.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>FOr ceaſed, read <hi>ceaſeth,</hi> pag. 10. l. 7. f. either, <hi>eithers,</hi> 20.25. f. appointed, <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed,</hi> 46.6. add <hi>evidenced,</hi> 63.9. put out <hi>it,</hi> 84.24. for good r <hi>burt,</hi> 98.5. f. their, <hi>there,</hi> 103.28. adde <hi>ſo,</hi> 110.13. f. wiſteſt, <hi>wiltſt,</hi> 115.18. f. 6, read 5.141.27. f. cut, <hi>call,</hi> 152.14.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:184293:8"/>
            <head>THE DROVSIE DISEASE. Or, An Alarme to awake Church-ſleepers.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The ſeverall kindes of ſleepe: and what-kinde is here treated of.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Leepe</hi> (as it is refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to <hi>man</hi>) is uſed in <hi>Scripture,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The ſeveral kindes of ſleepe.</note> either properly, or figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Properly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The proper acception thereof.</note> for <hi>that naturall reſt which God hath appointed for the continuing and moiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:184293:9"/>of naturall heat; the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing of the wearied ſpirits; the quickening and ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the weake members, and the preſervation of wearied Nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is occaſioned</hi> by vapours and fumes riſing from the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack to the head,<note place="margin">Whence it commeth.</note> where through coldneſſe of the braine they become congealed, and ſo ſtop the conduits and wayes of the ſenſes, that they become unable to execute their office, and may ſeeme for a time to be tied and bound up, which is therefore not without cauſe tearmed of ſome:<note place="margin">Ariſt. de ſom. &amp; vig.</note> 
                  <hi>The bond of the ſenſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hereof</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> is the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> (even the <hi>Father of lights,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Author thereof. Iam. 1.17. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Homer.</hi> Mat. 5.45.</note> 
                  <hi>from whom every good gift, and every perfect gift commeth downe</hi>) who (as <hi>hee maketh his Sunne to riſe on the evill, and on the good, and ſendeth raine on the juſt, and on the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt</hi>) equally communicated
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:184293:9"/>this bleſſing to good and bad, yet is it not more common then neceſſarie, for, <hi>It helpeth and perfecteth digestion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">How need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full it is.</note> 
                  <hi>recovereth ſtrength, refreſheth the body, reviveth the mind, pacifieth an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, driveth away ſorrow, and bringeth the whole man to good ſtate and temperature,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that of the <hi>Poet;</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>Thou reſt of things,<note place="margin">Somne, quies rerum, placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſime Somne Deorum, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Ovid. metant. lib. <hi>11. Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>
                           </hi> G. Sandys.</note> moſt meeke of all the Gods:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>O ſleepe,</hi> the peace of mindes, from whoſe abods</l>
                     <l>Care ever flies: restoring the decay</l>
                     <l>Of toyle-tir'd limbs to labour-burdening day.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Yea, as without this man could not conſiſt, (for
<q>
                     <l>There is no creature that can alwayes last,<note place="margin">Quod care<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> alternâ requie durabile non eſt, Ovid, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. <hi>4.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which wholly of his ſleepe is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſt.)</l>
                  </q> So for the fruition thereof, hee hath in a manner no leſſe time
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:184293:10"/>allotted unto him, then for the workes of his calling (for <hi>this</hi> craveth the <hi>night,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 104.23</note> as <hi>thoſe</hi> the <hi>day</hi>) yea as it is uſed, or rather abuſed,<note place="margin">Pars humanae melior vitae, Senec.</note> it is <hi>the better part of mans life,</hi> during the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance whereof (which is at the leaſt <hi>the one halfe of mans life</hi>) there is no difference betweene <hi>maſters</hi> and <hi>ſervants, kings</hi> and <hi>beggers;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dimidio vitae nihil differunt foelices ab in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foelicibus. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſ. Chil.</note> 
                  <hi>Craeſus</hi> and <hi>Codrus.</hi> as well <hi>thoſe</hi> as <hi>theſe</hi> entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>ſame;</hi> or rather with a kind of willing unwillingneſſe, nill they, will they, ſubjecting themſelves <hi>hereunto.</hi> Hereof another <hi>Poet</hi> ſpeaking to, and of <hi>ſleepe.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Thou charme to all our cares,<note place="margin">Tu<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ô domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, ſomne malorum, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies animi, &amp;c. Senec. Her. fur. act. <hi>4. tranſlated by Maſter</hi> G. Sandys.</note> that art</l>
                  <l>Of human life the better part:</l>
                  <l>Wing'd iſſue of a peacefull mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</l>
                  <l>Of rigid death, the elder bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</l>
                  <l>Father of things, the life of port:</l>
                  <l>The dayes repoſe, and nights conſort.</l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:184293:10"/>
                  <l>To Kings and vaſſals equall free,</l>
                  <l>The labour-tir'd refreſht by thee.</l>
                  <l>Who man (whom death doth terrifie)</l>
                  <l>Inur'ſt continually to die.</l>
               </q>
               <p>This is either ordinary,<note place="margin">The kindes of ſleepe properly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. Sleepe, when lawfull.</note> or extraordinary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ordinary,</hi> lawfull, or unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lawfull,</hi> when</p>
               <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>Seaſonable,</hi> as in the night, implied in that of the Pſalmiſt. <hi>Man goeth forth to his worke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 104 23 1 Theſſ. 5.7.</note> 
                  <hi>and to his labour untill the eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi> And, in that of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>They that ſleepe, ſleepe, in the night.</hi> So in the time of weakneſſe, ſickneſſe, and ſuch other bodily infirmities, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be by day, or night.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  <hi>Moderate:</hi> Not ſo ſhort, as that thereupon our health is endangered, or ſo long, as that thereby we are hindered from the duties of our Calling.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:184293:11"/> 3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                  <hi>Sanctified by prayer,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which <hi>no creature of God is to be received.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.4, 5.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                  <hi>Occaſioned by the works of our Calling.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.12.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
                  <hi>Our ſoules are awake in the meditation of heavenly things;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 26.9. Gen. 28.12. Cant. 5.2.</note> as it was with <hi>Iacob,</hi> and the <hi>Spouſe</hi> in the <hi>Canticles,</hi> if that may bee underſtood of bodily reſt.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
                  <hi>Wee are therby the more fitted for the workes of our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">When un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawfull, when.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſeaſonable,</hi> as at pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and the preaching of the Word,<note place="margin">Col. 4.2. Iam. 1.19.</note> for wee are to <hi>watch</hi> in the <hi>one,</hi> and be <hi>ſwift to heare the other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  <hi>Jmmoderate,</hi> as the ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards in the Proverbs;<note place="margin">Prov. 6.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Yet a little ſleepe, a little ſlumber, a little folding of the hands to ſleepe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                  <hi>No bleſſing of God is cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved thereupon,</hi> which is too too uſuall with moſt.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:184293:11"/> 4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                  <hi>Following upon the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinne,</hi> as theirs, of whom <hi>Salomon, They ſleepe not, except they have done miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, and their ſleepe is taken away, unleſſe they cauſe ſome to fall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
                  <hi>Our ſoules during the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance thereof ſatiate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the ſeeming plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of ſinne,</hi> whereof our u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall <hi>dreames</hi> may ſufficiently informe us.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
                  <hi>Wee become thereby the more ſtrengthened to continue in ſin, and to commit the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Extraordinary,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Naturall meanes occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioning ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary ſleepe.</note> occaſioned either through <hi>naturall,</hi> or through <hi>ſupernaturall</hi> meanes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Naturall,</hi> through</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Care, and griefe,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> as was that of the <hi>Diſciples.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 22.45.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Wearineſſe,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> as was that of <hi>Siſera's.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Judg. 4.21.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Long watching,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> as was that of <hi>Eutychus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 20.9.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Intemperance,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> as was that of <hi>Noahs.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 9.24.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:184293:12"/> 5. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
                  <hi>Labour,</hi> according to that of the Preacher;<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.12.</note> 
                  <hi>The ſleepe of a labouring man is ſweet, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he eat little or much.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
                  <hi>Heate,</hi> as was that of <hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſheth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 4.5.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 
                  <hi>Artificiall Potions made of Poppy, Lettuce, &amp;c.</hi> which is brought to paſſe, ſometimes for a <hi>good end,</hi> as when <hi>meanes</hi> are uſed to bring ſicke, weake, and aged perſons into a <hi>ſleepe;</hi> Sometimes for a <hi>bad,</hi> as when <hi>Dalilah</hi> made <hi>Sampſon</hi> ſleepe,<note place="margin">Iudg. 16.19.</note> that ſhee might betray him into the hands of his enemies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Supernaturall,</hi> as which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth immediatly of God, and that ſometimes on the <hi>godly,</hi> as on <hi>Adam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 2.21. Gen. 15.12.</note> when <hi>Hevah</hi> was formed; and on <hi>Abraham</hi> when God confirmed his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to him by a viſion; Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times on the <hi>ungodly,</hi> as on <hi>Saul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 26.12</note> when <hi>David</hi> tooke his Speare, ad the cruiſe of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which ſtood at his bolſter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Figuratively,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The accepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſleepe</note> and that as well
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:184293:12"/>in reſpect of the <hi>godly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">figuratively taken in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the godly.</note> and the <hi>ungodly ſeverally,</hi> as in reſpect of both <hi>joyntly</hi> conſidered,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Severally,</hi> In reſpect of the <hi>godly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>For abundant proſperity,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>tranquillitie, peace of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;</hi> quietneſſe, and reſt of minde, voide of carking care, and free from ſuch diſtractions, as during the ſtate of Nature diſquiet the whole man; <hi>I laid me downe and ſlept,</hi> ſaid <hi>David.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 3.5.</note> And againe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 1 27.2.</note> 
                  <hi>He giveth his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved ſleepe.</hi> Agreeable herre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto is that of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezech. 34.2</note> 
                  <hi>They ſhall dwell ſafely in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, and ſleepe in the woods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>For a ſpirituall ſlumber,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  <hi>and drowſineſſe in the mind and heart touching heavenly things,</hi> occaſioned through abundance of peace and pleaſures, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with a Chriſtian may bee at ſometimes ſo overtaken, as that (though bodily awake) with <hi>David</hi> hee falleth into the ſleepe of ſinne.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 11.4.</note> Such was the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:184293:13"/>
                  <hi>Spouſes</hi> ſlumber.<note place="margin">Cant. 5.2.</note> I <hi>ſleepe</hi> (ſaith ſhe) <hi>but my heart waketh.</hi> Such alſo the ſlumber, even of the <hi>five wiſe virgins.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 25.5.</note> When the Soule (either through careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or by reaſon of ſome temptation) ceaſed from good, then doth it thus ſleepe. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of what one is there, which may not juſtly complaine? How often doth man ſeeme unto himſelfe, wiſe, juſt, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, rich in grace? how often goeth hee on in his vanitie glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying in the multitude of his ſpirituall riches, and ſaying in the pride of his heart,<note place="margin">Rev. 3.17.</note> 
                  <hi>I ſhall not be moved for ever, I am rich and increaſed with goods, and have need of nothing?</hi> but when hee ſhall awake, hee will be aſhamed of ſuch fancies and dreames.<note place="margin">The ungodly for ſin, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall.</note>
               </p>
               <p>In reſpect of the <hi>ungodly,</hi> and that as well for <hi>ſinne,</hi> as the <hi>effects</hi> of ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sinne,</hi> conſidered both in <hi>generall,</hi> and in <hi>particular.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:184293:13"/>
               <p> In <hi>Generall.</hi> As in that of the Apoſtle.<note place="margin">Rom. 13.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Now it is high time to awake out of ſleepe.</hi> And againe;<note place="margin">Eph. 5.14. 1 Theſ. 5.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Awake thou that ſleepeſt.</hi> And againe, <hi>let us not ſleepe as doe others.</hi> Neither is it without eſpeciall cauſe that <hi>ſinne</hi> is <hi>thus</hi> expreſſed,<note place="margin">Reſemblan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces betweene ſleepe and ſinne.</note> there being indeed betweene <hi>ſinne</hi> and <hi>ſleepe,</hi> no ſmall <hi>reſemblance</hi> as may thus appeare.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>Sleepe</hi> is <hi>naturall</hi> to the <hi>body:</hi> ſo is <hi>ſinne</hi> to the <hi>Soule.</hi> Naturally,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.5.</note> 
                  <hi>every imagination of the thoughts of our hearts is onely evill continually.</hi> Wee <hi>leave the paths of uprightneſſe to walke in the wayes of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 2.13.14. Iſa. 5.18.</note> 
                  <hi>wee rejoyce to doe evill, and delight in the frowardneſſe of the wicked, wee draw iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with cords of vanity, and ſinne as it were with a cart-rope.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  <hi>Sleepe</hi> ſteales upon man as it were by <hi>degrees,</hi> ſo in like manner doth <hi>ſinne.</hi> Suggeſtion produceth delight. Delight,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:184293:14"/>conſent; Conſent, act; Act, the habite thereof.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Man being overtaken with <hi>ſleepe,</hi> feares no danger, bee it never ſo neere, never ſo great, as the examples of <hi>Iſhboſheth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 4.6.</note> and <hi>Ionah</hi> witneſſe; ſo <hi>ſinne</hi> driveth into ſecurity.<note place="margin">Ionah 1.5.</note> 
                  <hi>We have made a covenant with death</hi> (ſaid ſome in the daies of <hi>Eſay</hi>) <hi>and with hell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 28.15.</note> 
                  <hi>are wee at an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement; when the over-flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſcourge ſhall paſſe through, it ſhall not come unto us.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable hereunto is that of the Lord by <hi>Amos,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Amos 9.10.</note> 
                  <hi>All the ſinners of my people ſhall die by the ſword, which ſay the evill ſhall not overtake, nor prevent us,</hi> of whom <hi>Zephaniah;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zeph. 1.12. Luk. 17.27, 28.</note> 
                  <hi>They ſay in their heart: The Lord will not doe good, neither will he doe evill.</hi> Of this ſort were the old <hi>world,</hi> and <hi>Sodomites.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> A man given to <hi>ſleepe,</hi> doth for the moſt part <hi>retyre</hi> himſelfe from the company, ſociety, and fellowſhip of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:184293:14"/>to ſome one corner or other, that ſo neither himſelfe may be perceived, nor his reſt diſturbed.<note place="margin">Lycoſt. Theat. vitae humanae.</note> Such a one alſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther affecteth <hi>light,</hi> nor <hi>noiſe,</hi> as <hi>Sibertus,</hi> who baniſhed dogs, and tradeſ-men from the place of his reſidence, leſt thereby his ſleepe ſhould be broke, agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto the Poets deſcription of ſleepe in theſe words;
<q>
                     <l>Neere the <hi>Cimmerians,</hi> lurkes a cave,<note place="margin">Eſt prope Cimmerios longo Spelun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca receſſu, mons cavus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Ovid. Met. <hi>11. Tranſlated by Maſter</hi> G. Sandys.</note> in ſleepe</l>
                     <l>And hollow hills; the manſion of dull <hi>ſleepe.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Not ſeene by Phoebus, when he mounts the skies</l>
                     <l>At height, nor ſtouping: gloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming miſts ariſe</l>
                     <l>From humide earth; which ſtill a twilight make</l>
                     <l>No creſted fowles ſhrill crowing here awake</l>
                     <l>The cheerefull morne, no bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſentinell</l>
                     <l>Here guards, nor geeſe, who wakefull dogs excell.</l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:184293:15"/>
                     <l>Beaſts tame, nor ſavge: no wind-ſhaken boughs,</l>
                     <l>Nor ſtrife of jarring tongues, with noiſes rouſe.</l>
                     <l>Secured eaſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>So <hi>ſinners</hi> (if not paſt ſhame) doe eſpecially in ſecret commit their villanies.<note place="margin">Ezech. 8.10.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 4.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Cain</hi> getteth his brother out into the fields, and then ſlayeth him.<note place="margin">Joſh 7.21.</note> 
                  <hi>Achan</hi> hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his ſtollen goods. <hi>Gehezi</hi> without the knowledge of his Maſter (as hee conceived) ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth money and raiment of <hi>Naaman,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 King. 5.24.</note> and <hi>they that are drunke</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>are drunke in the night.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.7.</note> And leſt they ſhould not thus ſleepe long enough, and ſafe enough, they ſtop the light of the Word, put out the light of their owne conſciences, and forbid even thoſe whoſe office it is to awake them out of ſleepe, to awake them till they pleaſe.<note place="margin">Ier. 44.16.</note> 
                  <hi>As for the word which thou haſt ſpoken to us in the name of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:184293:15"/>the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Amos 7.12, 13.</note> 
                  <hi>we will not hearken to thee,</hi> ſaid the people unto <hi>Ieremiah, O thou Seer</hi> (ſaid <hi>Amaziah</hi> unto <hi>Amos</hi>) <hi>goe flee thee away into the land of Iudah, and there eat bread, and prophecie there, but prophecie not againe any more in Bethel, for it is the kings Chappel, and it is the Kings Court.</hi> Yea, as a man being aſleepe, doth for the moſt part take it ill, when he is awaked; ſo a ſinner when hee is called upon to forſake his ſinnes;<note place="margin">Prov. 6.10.</note> 
                  <hi>yet a little ſleep</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a little ſlumber, a little fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the hands to ſleep. The time is not come,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hag. 1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>the time that the Lords houſe ſhould be built,</hi> ſaid the people unto <hi>Haggai. Haſt thou found me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King. 21.20.</note> 
                  <hi>O mine enemy,</hi> ſaid <hi>Ahab</hi> unto <hi>Elijah.</hi> If <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> ſay unto <hi>Herod,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 14, 3.4.</note> 
                  <hi>It is not lawfull for thee to have thy brother Philips wife;</hi> hee will lay hold on him, and put him in priſon. If <hi>Paul</hi> reaſon of righteouſneſſe, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:184293:16"/>and judgement to come; <hi>Felix</hi> will tremble, and anſwer,<note place="margin">Act. 24.25.</note> 
                  <hi>Goe thy way for this time, when I have a convenient ſeaſon, I will call for thee.</hi> If <hi>Micaiah</hi> detect the forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and falſhood of <hi>Zedekiah, Zedekiah</hi> will ſmite him on the cheeke,<note place="margin">1 King. 22.24.</note> ſaying, <hi>Which way went the Spirit of the Lord from me to ſpeake unto thee?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
                  <hi>Sleepe,</hi> during its conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, <hi>hindereth</hi> and letteth men, even from the <hi>Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance</hi> of civill <hi>offices,</hi> as the Souldier from fighting, the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer from working, the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter and Maſon from buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and the like; ſo cannot wee by reaſon of <hi>ſinne</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme any thing which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God (though the ſame bee in it ſelfe lawfull and warrantable) till wee be raiſed there-from.<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.16, 17.</note> 
                  <hi>What hast thou to doe</hi> (ſaith God unto the wicked) <hi>to declare my ſtatutes, or that thou ſhouldeſt take my
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:184293:16"/>Covenant in thy mouth? Seeing thou hateſt inſtruction, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteſt my words behind thee.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jſa. 1.11</note> 
                  <hi>To what purpoſe is the multitude of your ſacrifices unto mee?</hi> (ſaith the Lord, unto his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) <hi>I am full of the burnt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of rams,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jſa. 1.15.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c. your hands are full of bloud.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 4.5.</note> As <hi>Cain</hi> could not offer up an accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſacrifice unto God, being aſleepe in ſinne; ſo whileſt it goeth over our ſoules, binding up the faculties of the ſame, and bringing an heavineſſe, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deadneſſe into all the powers thereof, we are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unfit to goe about the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of an holy life. Hence commeth it to paſſe, that the <hi>mind</hi> never thinketh ſeriouſly of God: the <hi>conſcience</hi> never or ſeldome accuſeth for ſinnes committed: the <hi>will</hi> never or ſeldome willeth that which is truly good: the <hi>affections</hi> ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or never are moved at Gods word or workes, yea, ſo
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:184293:17"/>long as it beareth ſway over us, we can neither pray aright, heare the Word aright, nor rightly performe any other dutie.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> In <hi>ſleepe</hi> wee doe often conceive our condition to bee better, then indeed it is. The poore man dreameth of riches, the ſicke of health, the impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned of liberty, the hunger-ſtarved of dainty fare, deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelves with a kind of content, in the (imaginary) fruition of theſe things. So doth a ſinner bleſſe himſelfe in his courſe. <hi>I am</hi> (ſaith <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi>) <hi>and none elſe beſide me:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jſa. 47.8.</note> 
                  <hi>I ſhall not ſit as a widow, neither ſhall I know the loſſe of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 12.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Soule</hi> (ſaid the rich man in the Goſpel, to his owne ſoule) <hi>thou haſt much goods laid up for many yeares,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 18.11.</note> 
                  <hi>take thine eaſe, eat, drinke, and be merry. God I thanke thee</hi> (ſaid the vaine-glorious, ſelfe-conceited, hypocriticall Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee)
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:184293:17"/>
                  <hi>that J am not as other men are, extortioners, unjuſt, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, or even as this Publican.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In particular.</note>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Particular</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. For <hi>careleſneſſe.</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>Sloath</hi> and <hi>negligence</hi> whether in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 56.10.</note> or <hi>people. His watchmen are blind</hi> (ſaith <hi>Eſay</hi>) <hi>they are all ignorant: they are all dumbe dogs, they cannot barke, ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, lying downe, loving to ſlumber.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſ. 7.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Their baker ſleepeth all the night,</hi> ſaith <hi>Hoſea. But while men ſlept</hi> (ſaith our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour) <hi>his enemy came,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 13.25.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſowed tares among the wheate, and went his way.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 6.9.</note> 
                  <hi>How long wilt thou ſleepe, O ſluggard?</hi> (ſaith the Wiſe man) <hi>when wilt thou ariſe out of thy ſleepe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> For <hi>whoredome</hi> or <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe. Come</hi> (ſaid <hi>Lots</hi> eldeſt daughter unto her ſiſter) <hi>Let us make our father drinke wine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 19.32.</note> 
                  <hi>and we will lye</hi> (or ſleepe) <hi>with him, that we may preſerve ſeed of our father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>effects of ſinne.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The effects of ſinne.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:184293:18"/> 1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 4.19.</note> On the <hi>Soule</hi> (even in this life) a ſpirituall <hi>lethargie</hi> or <hi>deadneſſe</hi> of <hi>heart</hi> by the <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> of <hi>ſinne,</hi> when as the heart is made <hi>past feeling,</hi> and altogether <hi>ſenſleſſe,</hi> through <hi>continuance,</hi> therein. Whereof <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 29.10.</note> 
                  <hi>For the Lord hath pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out upon you the ſpirit of deepe ſleepe, and hath cloſed your eyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Perpetuall and irrevoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>deſtruction,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 76.5. Pſal. 13.3.</note> whereof the Pſalmiſt, <hi>The ſtout-hearted are ſpoyled, they have ſlept their ſleepe.</hi> And againe, <hi>lighten mine eyes, lest J ſleepe the ſleepe of death.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 51.39.</note> So the Lord by <hi>Ieremiah, Jn their heat J will make their feaſts, and I will make them drunken, that they may rejoyce, and ſleepe a perpetuall ſleepe, and not wake, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ioyntly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The godly and ungodly joyntly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered.</note> in reſpect both of the <hi>godly</hi> and <hi>ungodly,</hi> either <hi>death</hi> being by <hi>ſleepe</hi> ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantly expreſſed.</p>
               <p>The <hi>godlies,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King. 2.10</note> as <hi>David ſlept
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:184293:18"/>with his fathers.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 11.11. Mat. 27.52.</note> 
                  <hi>Our friend Lazarus ſleepeth, and the graves were opened, and many bodies of ſaints which ſlept a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe.</hi> The <hi>ungodlies,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King. 14 20 1 King. 15.8 1 King. 16.6.</note> as <hi>Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam ſlept with his fathers. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biam ſlept with his fathers. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſha ſlept with his fathers, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> But as <hi>David</hi> of <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 3.33.</note> 
                  <hi>(died Abner as a foole dieth?)</hi> Is there no difference betweene thoſe, and theſe, (the godly and the ungodly) in death?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> In ſome reſpect there is no difference at all,<note place="margin">Sol.</note> according to that of <hi>Solomon;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 2.16.</note> 
                  <hi>How dieth the wiſe man? as the foole.</hi> But in others very great, according to that of the ſame Author.<note place="margin">Prov. 14.32.</note> 
                  <hi>The wicked is driven away in his wickedneſſe, but the righteous hath hope in his death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Their <hi>agreement</hi> conſiſteth in theſe particulars.<note place="margin">Wherein that death of the godly and wicked agree.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Our <hi>beds</hi> repreſent our <hi>graves:</hi> the <hi>ſheetes</hi> wherein wee lye our <hi>winding-ſheets,</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:184293:19"/>wherein were ſhall bee <hi>wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped.</hi> The <hi>cloaths</hi> that lye on us, the <hi>clods</hi> of <hi>earth</hi> that ſhall bee caſt upon us, when wee are laid in our graves, yea as they that are aſleepe are for the time <hi>voide</hi> of care, and <hi>inſenſible</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>joy</hi> or <hi>paine,</hi> neither being affected with the <hi>miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> of others to mourne with them, nor with their <hi>proſperity</hi> to rejoyce with them, but (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their eyes bound up from ſeeing, their eares from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, as their other ſenſes from the execution of their ſeverall functions) are wholly <hi>ignorant</hi> of things done about them, ſo is it with thoſe that are <hi>dead.</hi> To this purpoſe <hi>Job,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 3.12, 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Why did the knees prevent me? or why the breaſts that I ſhould ſucke? for now ſhould I have lyen ſtill, and beene quiet, I ſhould have ſlept, then had I beene at reſt.</hi> And <hi>Iſaiah</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">Iſa. 63.16.</note> 
                  <hi>that now Abraham is ignorant of us, and Iſrael doth not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:184293:19"/>us.</hi> Hence it is,<note place="margin">Iob 7.2.</note> 
                  <hi>that as a ſervant earnestly deſireth the ſhadow, and as an hireling loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth for the reward of his worke, ſo not a few</hi> doe daily gape for death, that thereby they may bee freed from their troubles. <hi>It is now enough, O Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King. 19.4</note> (ſaid <hi>Elijah</hi>) <hi>take away my life, for I am no better then my fathers.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jonah 4.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Take J beſeech thee my life from me</hi> (ſaid <hi>Jonah</hi>) <hi>for it is better for me to die, then to live.</hi> And <hi>in thoſe dayes</hi> (ſaith 8. <hi>John,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 9.6.</note> namely when unto the locuſts, that came out of the bottomleſſe pit, power was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to torment thoſe men which have not the ſeale of God on their foreheads) <hi>ſhall men ſeeke death, and ſhall not find it, and ſhall deſire to die, and death ſhall flye from them.</hi> Agreeable hereunto is that of <hi>Philo;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Anton. &amp; Max. ſer. de ſomno. Aelian. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> who being asked what ſleepe was, anſwered, <hi>The i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of death, and reſt of the ſenſes;</hi> and that of <hi>Gorgias,</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:184293:20"/>who being very aged, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling deadly ſleepe or death to creepe on him, unto a friend, who asked him how hee did, anſwered,<note place="margin">Braſ. lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Sleepe now begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to commend me unto his brother,</hi> and that of <hi>Epaminon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> who having ſlaine one of the watch whom hee found ſleeping, thus juſtified his fact, <hi>Such a one, as I found him</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I have left him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Euſtat. ad Hom. Ibid. Tertull. de a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nima, Chryſ. ad pop. ant. homil. <hi>5.</hi> Ariſt. lib. <hi>19.</hi> de animal.</note> To this purpoſe is it, that of ſome ſleepe and death are ſaid to <hi>bee brethren or couſin-Germans,</hi> Sleepe <hi>Deaths looking-glaſſe, death a ſleepe longer then uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,</hi> yea ſleepe a <hi>kind of middle thing betweene death and life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  <hi>Sleepe</hi> as it is common to all men, and cannot bee dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven away or avoided of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, how ſparing ſoever, or well-ſpenders of time,<note place="margin">Heb. 9.27. Rom. 5.12. Pſal. 89.48.</note> ſo <hi>it is appointed unto him once to die. Death paſſeth upon all men,</hi> and <hi>what man is he that ſhall not ſee death?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:184293:20"/> 3. <hi>Sleepe,</hi> though uſually it commeth by degrees, as after labour, meat, wearineſſe, wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and the like; yet doth it often ſteale on men at una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares; So <hi>death</hi> though uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,<note place="margin">1 King. 13.24.</note> and by courſe of nature it followeth ſickneſſe as the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner thereof, yet ſeazeth it often on men both good and bad on the very ſudden.<note place="margin">Act. 5.5.10.</note> So did in on the man of God that came unto <hi>Bethel,</hi> ſo on <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 12.19.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Then ſaid God unto the rich man; Thou foole, this night ſhall thy ſoule be required of thee,</hi> when he had ſaid unto his ſoule; <hi>Soule, thou haſt much goods laid up for many yeares, take thine eaſe, eate, drinke, and be merry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                  <hi>Sleepe</hi> is proper to the <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> not the <hi>ſoule,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cord vigila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, etiam cùm corpore dormimus, Aug. de verb. dom. Ser. <hi>22. Iſa. 26.19.</hi>
                  </note> (for <hi>even then are we to be awake in ſoule, when wee ſleepe in body</hi>) ſo <hi>dieth</hi> man in reſpect of his <hi>body,</hi> not his <hi>ſoule.</hi> Though the body reſts and dwells in the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:184293:21"/>duſt of the earth, yet doth not the ſoule ſo reſt. <hi>The duſt</hi> (that is the body) <hi>returneth to the earth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.7.</note> 
                  <hi>as it was, and the ſpirit returneth unto God, who gave it;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Anima quieti nunquam ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedit. Tertul. de anima.</note> yea, if the ſoule doe yea, if the ſoule doe not now ſleepe, whilſt it is in the priſon of the body, much leſſe ſhall it, being freed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from. As the ſoules of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are carried into heaven,<note place="margin">Luk, 16, 22.</note> ſo are the ſoules of the ungodly into hell, eithers bodyes in the meane time remaining in their graves.<note place="margin">Hiſt. Florent. lib. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> As <hi>Cofimo</hi> the <hi>Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> to ſome Rebels that ſent him word <hi>they ſlept not,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that <hi>hee beleeved the ſame, becauſe their ſleepe was taken from them.</hi> So may it be affirmed of mens ſoules, that as <hi>here</hi> they cannot <hi>ſleepe,</hi> ſo <hi>hereafter</hi> they cannot <hi>die.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
                  <hi>Sleepe,</hi> though it bee of longer continuance with ſome, then with others, yet laſteth it not <hi>alwayes</hi> with any; even the ſluggard being at the length
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:184293:21"/>awaked, or awaking there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from, ſo <hi>death</hi> muſt at the laſt reſtore her dead, how long ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>everthey have beene under the power, and in the poſſeſſion thereof,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.52.</note> 
                  <hi>For the trumpet ſhall ſound</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>and the dead ſhall be raiſed incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible, and we ſhall be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</hi> Agreeable hereunto is the of S, <hi>Iohn;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 20.13.</note> 
                  <hi>And the ſea gave up the dead which were in it, and death and hell delivered up the dead which were in them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>difference</hi> between them in theſe.<note place="margin">Wherin they differ.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Though ſuch as are aſleep may of ſhall awake, yet doth not their awaking prove alike comfortable (for <hi>Pharaohs Butler</hi> was reſtored, and his <hi>Baker</hi> hanged, according to <hi>Ioſephs</hi> interpretation of their dreames.) So both the ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and the godly die, yet doth not either death prove advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious.<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.28.</note> 
                  <hi>The houre is comming
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:184293:22"/>in the which all that are in the graves ſhall heare the voyce of the Sonne of man, and ſhall come forth, they that have done good unto the reſurrection of life, and they that have done evill unto the reſurrection of damnation,</hi> Saith our Saviour himſelfe; All the <hi>ten virgins</hi> which ſlumbered (as well the <hi>wiſe</hi> as the <hi>fooliſh</hi>) aroſe,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.7.10.12.</note> but the <hi>wiſe</hi> onely went in with the Bridegroome unto the mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, the <hi>others</hi> being excluded; <hi>Depart from me ye cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 25.34.41.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall it be ſaid unto the wicked on the day of judgement;</hi> but unto the godly, <hi>Come yee bleſſed of my Father.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1 Cor. 15.56.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chryſ. ad Heb. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eſt.</note> Unto theſe death is not as death (as having the <hi>ſting</hi> thereof removed, which is <hi>ſinne</hi>) but as a ſweet ſleep, unto thoſe it is otherwiſe: even <hi>of fearfull things the moſt fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</hi> Thoſe loſe, but theſe gaine thereby, a palace for a priſon, reſt for labour, liberty for bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, God for men, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:184293:22"/>of Angels for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of ſinners, and finally, heaven for earth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As <hi>ſleepe</hi> proveth unto many fatall, wherein they die, and from which they never riſe; ſo unto the ungodly the death of the body is a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner of that ſecond death, the death both of body and ſoule; under which they ſhall lye world without end. But it is not ſo unto Gods children. Thereby is put an end unto all their miſeries,<note place="margin">Rev. 14.13.</note> for <hi>they reſt from their labours, neither doe they hunger any more, or thirſt any more, and all teares are wiped from their eyes.</hi> Thereby are they freed from all <hi>ſorts of ſinnes:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 6.7</note> (for <hi>hee that is dead is freed from ſinne</hi>) thereby from the <hi>being of ſinne:</hi> from the <hi>infection of ſinne:</hi> from the <hi>guilt of ſinne:</hi> from <hi>temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> unto <hi>ſinne:</hi> from the <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, dominion,</hi> and <hi>rule</hi> of <hi>ſinne:</hi> from the <hi>imputation</hi> of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:184293:23"/>
                  <hi>ſinne:</hi> from the <hi>reward</hi> or <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous effect</hi> and conſequents of <hi>ſinne,</hi> and that <hi>wholly, fully, perpetually.</hi> Thereby from all <hi>ſorts of croſſes.</hi> Thereby from <hi>all ſorts of feares.</hi> Thereby from all ſorts <hi>of cares;</hi> In a word, thereby freed from <hi>all ſorts of evill,</hi> paſt, preſent and to come.<note place="margin">Pſa. 57.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>They lie downe in ſure and certaine hope of reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to eternall life,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">I Cor. 15.42 43, 44.</note> 
                  <hi>Their bodyes are ſowne in corruption, but raiſed in incorruption, ſowne in diſhonour, but raiſed in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; ſowne in weakneſſe, but rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in power; ſowne naturall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes,</hi> (as many goe heavily to bed) <hi>but raiſed ſpirituall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes,</hi> when through the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous beames of the Sunne of righteouſneſſe ſhining on them, they ſhall fully recollect both their ſpirits and ſtrength, in all which reſpects that of <hi>Salomon</hi> may bee applyed unto them, that <hi>Their day of death is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then the day wherein they were borne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:184293:23"/> 3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> As every one is not alike willing to ſleepe, eſpecially ſuch as are unuſually terrified by dreames; ſo neither are all alike willing to die. The god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wait for death:<note place="margin">Iob 7.14.</note> 
                  <hi>All the dayes of my appointed time will I wait</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iob) till my change come;</hi> yea,<note place="margin">Iob 14.14.</note> with the Apoſtle <hi>deſire to be diſſolved,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 1.23. Heb. 9.27.</note> 
                  <hi>and to bee with Chriſt,</hi> But the ungodly whoſe conſciences tell them <hi>that after death commeth judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 24.25.</note> doe with <hi>Foelix</hi> tremble at the very mentioning there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: yet (how loath ſoever to undergoe it, what paines or charges ſoever they are at, when they feele it or feare it approaching to remove it and put it off) doe moſt of them even willingly (as it were) through intemperancie, incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tincencie, carking cares, and ſuch like courſes bring it upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> As through <hi>ſleepe</hi> they that are in miſery are fitted and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:184293:24"/>enabled to undergoe more mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, and they that are in a good condition become capable of more happineſſe, ſo through death are the ungodly, as it were, fitted for hell, the godly for heaven; thoſe for uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable miſery, theſe for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable happineſſe.</p>
               <p>Take we it in this <hi>Treatiſe</hi> in its <hi>proper</hi> ſignification,<note place="margin">Sleepe how taken in this Treatiſe.</note> but for ſuch a <hi>ſleepe</hi> as is altogether <hi>unlawfull,</hi> howſoever <hi>ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> and <hi>common,</hi> for then to <hi>ſleepe,</hi> when wee ought to bee <hi>ſwiſt to heare,</hi> and then to bee <hi>drowſie,</hi> when it concernes us to be <hi>moſt vigilant</hi> (as at the <hi>prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching</hi> of the <hi>word,</hi> and <hi>prayer</hi>) who will not judge the ſame <hi>unreaſonable,</hi> and ſo neither <hi>lawfull</hi> nor <hi>warrantable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Be this then, this unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, unlawfull, unwarrantable kind of <hi>ſleepe,</hi> or rather ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping evill <hi>(ſleeping at Church)</hi> this inordinate, ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary bodily drouſineſſe, I ſay,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:184293:24"/>whereby the Word read or preached becommeth wholly ineffectuall, and no bleſſing from God, but rather an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted curſe can bee expected thereupon, the <hi>ſubject</hi> of this <hi>diſcourſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> How convenient and neceſſary it is to handle this Argument.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Either needs any to wonder that this ſhould bee medled withall,<note place="margin">Reaſons ſhewing the utility, and neceſſary of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe.</note> or conceive him to have little to doe, unleſſe to keepe himſelfe awake, which buſieth himſelfe about ſuch a ſleepy ſubject. Theſe with the like warranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reaſons will (queſtionleſſe) juſtifie our proceeding.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Becauſe <hi>this is by moſt no otherwiſe</hi> (if at all) <hi>medled withall, then by a bare curſory
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:184293:25"/>ſpeaking againſt it,</hi> and that not of ſet purpoſe, but occaſionally upon the view of ſome one or other ſleeping; yea, and that but in generall tearmes, which how fruitleſſe and ineffectuall it proveth to reclaime any there-from daily experience ſheweth. As therefore for the ſubduing of other vices,<note place="margin">Iſa, 28.10.</note> there muſt bee both <hi>Precept upon precept, and lyne upon lyne,</hi> ſo muſt there be for the ſubduing of <hi>this.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Becauſe <hi>there are ſo many which offend herein, and yet thinke, that either they have not at all, or but a little offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</hi> Thoſe ſtanding upon their juſtification; Theſe go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about to excuſe their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe. Such had need to bee wrought on, brought on, to ſee the greatneſſe of this ſinne,<note place="margin">Gen. 19.20.</note> and that (as <hi>Lot</hi> of <hi>Zoar</hi>) they may not conceit, that it is but <hi>a little one.</hi> Before thoſe muſt the <hi>evils</hi> hereof bee laid open,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:184293:25"/>
                  <hi>Reaſons</hi> diſſwading from the ſame be propounded, as in like manner, their ſeverall <hi>objections</hi> to the contrary, plainly and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidly diſſolved.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Becauſe <hi>there are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, which being cuſtomarily ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted hereunto (yet excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly deſirous and willing to leave the ſame) are notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding wholly ignorant how to effect it.</hi> Thoſe muſt bee made acquainted as well with the <hi>Cauſes</hi> hereof, as <hi>Remedies</hi> how to be rid of the ſame.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Becauſe <hi>there are but a few, which doe truly take notice of the danger enſuing hereby, or conſider the wrongs occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned through the ſame.</hi> The ignorant therefore and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe are to bee ſhewed, that hereby they wrong the bleſſed Trinitie, hereby are ſtumbling blocks unto others, which through their evill example in this kind prove no leſte wicked then themſelves. Hereby the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:184293:26"/>Word becommeth ineffectuall, and the Miniſters thereof diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged: yea, that this is one maine cauſe, why they doe ſo long continue in their ſinnes, to the griefe and hurt of their owneſoules.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
                  <hi>Becauſe this ſinne cannot be ſo well met withall by ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king againſt it, as by writing,</hi> For if a Miniſter ſhould in his Sermon, when an occaſion is preſented unto him (as when is there not?) inveigh againſt the ſame, hee might haply through weakneſſe or want of memory forget himſelfe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bee able againe without much adoe to come to his mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or rather be forced by new objects of drowſineſſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new his reproofes, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually to goe on in that argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; yea, though there were no feare of ſuch deſtruction, yet in as much as a Miniſter is not to nominate any of his auditors in particular. Neither haply
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:184293:26"/>(if it were lawfull for him to name them) knoweth hee his Auditors by name, though hee ſhould obſerve them to bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepe, his reproofes muſt bee generall, which (as in other things) who doth not almoſt put from himſelf, as if they did not at-all concerne him, or the Miniſter therein had no ayme at him?<note place="margin">Mat. 26.21.</note> Our Saviour having informed his Diſciples in generall tearmes (not parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularizing the name of any) that <hi>one of them ſhould betray him;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſe. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>Indas</hi> thereupon (who indeed was (the villaine, the man aymed at) could ſay not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, <hi>Is it I Maſter?</hi> ſo doe too too many in the caſe we have in hand.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
                  <hi>Becauſe there are no law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meanes</hi> (who will judge this unlawfull?<note place="margin">Deut. 22.1, 2, 3.</note>) <hi>which Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are not to uſe for the good one of another;</hi> Yea, if the Lord require of us the manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of brotherly love, even
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:184293:27"/>in ſuch things as concerne our neighbours (our enemies) e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtate,<note place="margin">Deut. 22.1, 2, 3.</note> much more doth hee it in ſuch things as concerne the welfare of their bodies, and if of their bodies, much more of their ſoules. Now what can be more advantagious unto their ſoules, then their carefull and conſcionable hearing of the Word? and how can they thus heare it, if they ſleepe thereat? and ſleepe they will, if meanes be not uſed to keepe them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake. As therefore one of the <hi>Perſian</hi> kings Chamberlaines was every morning to come unto his Maſters bed-ſide, and to awake him with theſe words;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Plut.</note> 
                  <hi>Ariſe O King, and be carefull of the buſineſſes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of</hi> Meſoromaſdes <hi>willed thee to take care;</hi> So may every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian (muſt every Chriſtian) carefully uſe meanes whereby as well to with-hold them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as withdraw others from this ſleeping evill. May
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:184293:27"/>it be lawfull in the words of <hi>Solomon</hi> to rowſe up the ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard?<note place="margin">Prov. 6.9.</note> 
                  <hi>How long wilt thou ſleep O fluggard? when wilt thou ariſe out of thy ſleepe?</hi> And will any judge this unlawfull? yea, ſhould wee not thus ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour our ſelves according to our abilities to prevent, or to amend the ſame, we might aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well be truly reputed as juſtly puniſhed for partaking with others in ſinne, which (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to S. <hi>Pauls</hi> caveat) who is not bound carefully to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voide?<note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.22.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Becauſe,<note place="margin">Canon 18.</note> 
                  <hi>this is a breach of one of our Church-Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> which requireth, that <hi>None, either man, woman, or child, of what calling ſoever ſhall bee otherwiſe buſied</hi> (in time of Service or Sermon) <hi>then in quiet attendance to heare, marke and underſtand that which is read, preached, or miniſtred;</hi> And that <hi>They ſhall not diſturbe the Service or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:184293:28"/>by walking and talking, or any other way.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Becauſe as toward the rearing up of the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 35.22.</note> ſome brought <hi>bracelets, and earings,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 23.</note> 
                  <hi>and rings, and tablets, all jewels of gold,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 24:</note> and the <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers brought Onix-ſtones, and ſtones to be ſet for the Ephod, and for the breſt-plate;</hi> So o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers brought <hi>goats haire, and red skinnes of rams, and bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers skinnes;</hi> neither of which were rejected, but the offerings of either accepted (yea, and our <hi>Saviour</hi> did more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the <hi>poore widow,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 21.3.</note> for her <hi>two mites</hi> which ſhee caſt into the treaſury, then the <hi>rich</hi> for their liberall <hi>offerings,</hi> inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as they <hi>out of their abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance caſt into the offerings of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 4.</note> 
                  <hi>but ſhe of her penurie caſt in all the living ſhe had.</hi>) So if towards the encreaſe of the kingdome of Chriſt, and buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding up one another in our moſt holy faith, Some with the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:184293:28"/>
                  <hi>Captaine</hi> of the <hi>Aramites</hi> medled onely with the <hi>king</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King. 22, 32.</note> that is, <hi>great ſinnes,</hi> as ſwearing, adultery, murther, and the like, (as ſome worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and profitably have done) or detect and confute <hi>hereſies,</hi> reſolve <hi>caſes</hi> of <hi>conſcience;</hi> ſet forth large <hi>commentaries</hi> on the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and handle <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies</hi> (which are as gold, ſilver, and pretious ſtones) and all to the ſingular good of Gods people, why may not others bring their goates haire? I meane, diſcover and oppoſe, even the <hi>pettieſt</hi> offences. As there muſt bee <hi>meat for men,</hi> (of which kind are the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Councels, Schoole-men,</hi> large <hi>Commentaries'</hi> on the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> &amp;c.) So muſt there <hi>milke for babes,</hi> of which kind are <hi>Catechiſmes,</hi> plaine <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, Prayer bookes,</hi> books of <hi>Meditations,</hi> and ſuch like ſhort godly <hi>diſcourſes,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of queſtionleſſe no ſmall bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:184293:29"/>daily ariſeth, as their often impreſſions cleerely witneſſe. Nay, even the greateſt ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and moſt learned men have not thought their time II be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed in writing on ſuch low diſcourſes (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpake of the <hi>hyſope that ſpringeth out of the wall</hi>) to the capacitie of the meaneſt.<note place="margin">1 King. 4.33.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Whence it is, that Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleeping is ſo ordinary, and uſuall.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>cauſes</hi> hereof (not to mention Gods juſtice on the contemners of his Word, who for the moſt part being come to Church are caſt into ſuch a deepeſleepe, that though they have both eyes and eares, yet (for the time) they are depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:184293:29"/>of the uſe of either, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeeing with the one, nor hearing with the other, of whom it may be ſaid as of <hi>Saul</hi> and his <hi>troups,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 26.12.</note> 
                  <hi>a deepe ſleepe of God as upon them that they doe not awake;</hi>) The <hi>Cauſes</hi> I ſay hereof may he reduced eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally into theſe three;</p>
               <p>The firſt arifing from <hi>Satan.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The cauſes of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleeping.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond ariſing from <hi>our ſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third ariſing from <hi>others,</hi> both <hi>Preachers</hi> and <hi>people.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 1. <hi>Satan.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">From Satan.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>As <hi>Dalilah</hi> made <hi>Sampſon</hi> ſleepe on her lap to the loſſe as well of his liberty,<note place="margin">Iudg. 16.19.</note> as life: ſo doth <hi>Satan</hi> rocke us aſleepe at Church, that hee may leade us captive at his pleaſure, to the utter and everlaſting ruine both of bodies, and ſoules. Hereof tooke <hi>Machetes</hi> (of whom <hi>Caſſianus</hi> maketh mention) good notice,<note place="margin">Lorinus in Acta Apoſt. pag. <hi>591.</hi>
                     </note> for obſerving his
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:184293:30"/>fellow. Monkes when hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſpeake unto them of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly things ſuddenly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon to fall aſleepe, but when of other matters, to lend their attentive eares, hee informed them that <hi>the ſame came of Satan;</hi> yea, how many are there found, which if they had no mind nor inclination to fleepe a day or two before, will notwithftanding ſleepe at Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Sermon? whence commeth it to paſſe? aſſuredly from Satan who is ready and buſie enough to beſprinkle their temples with his ſpirituall <hi>opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> of evill motions and ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions, and having maliciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enclined them to drowſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, diligently rocketh the cradle, that they may ſleepe the more ſoundly.<note place="margin">Who bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to paſſe.</note> This hee bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth diverſly to paſſe, as</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> By <hi>working with out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward meanes occaſioning ſleepe,</hi> ſuch as heat, weakneſſe, griefe, long watching, and the like.</p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:184293:30"/>
                  <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> By <hi>keeping men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in ignorance, or without the knowledge of the Word.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> By <hi>perſwading, that the Preacher is not worth the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,</hi> and ſo that <hi>his words are not to be regarded,</hi> or that <hi>in his Sermons he venteth his owne ſpleene and malice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> By <hi>propounding,</hi> that <hi>though the Miniſter ſhould preach never ſo well, and they ſhould give never ſo diligent heed thereunto,</hi> yet that <hi>it will be to no purpoſe, they being una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to conceive any thing by him delivered,</hi> which for the moſt part through his meanes in moſt proveth too too true.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> By <hi>working a generall diſlike of the Word preached, in reſpect of its oppoſition unto thoſe things, which are with moſt, in moſt requeſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> By <hi>drawing the atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and intention another way.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:184293:31"/>
                  <head>Sect. 2. <hi>Our ſelves.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">From our ſelves in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                     <hi>Through ſloathfulneſſe,</hi> according to that of <hi>Salomon,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pro. 19.15.</note> 
                     <hi>Slothfulneſſe caſteth into a deep ſleep,</hi> which may bee no leſſe appointed unto this, then unto any other. Hee that is ſloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full cannot but ſleepe whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he is. Neither the feare of danger, nor hope of reward will keepe him awake;<note place="margin">Languido ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ingenio, &amp; in ſomnum ituro. Senec. de Provid. cap. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </note> wee are all naturally of a very dull and drowſie diſpoſition, by reaſon of that lumpiſh fleſh of ours, that abideth much even in the beſt, by meanes whereof it commeth to paſſe, that wee doe often-times ſleepe and ſlumber be we never ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and diligent, much more being ſloathfull. As it is with drowſie perſons, if they ſit ſtill and doe nothing, they will ſoone fall aſleepe, ſo if we give our ſelves over to ſlothful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, wee ſhall ſoone be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:184293:31"/>with this diſmall ſleepe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                     <hi>Through careleſneſſe,</hi> or <hi>want of attention,</hi> when the mind is not ſet on its right ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, the preaching and reading of the Word, but roveth on by-matters, neither are the eyes fixed on the Preacher, but walke hither and thither, then is it no wonder but that ſleepe by degrees creepeth on. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have we caveats and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings propounded.<note place="margin">Rev. 2.7.</note> 
                     <hi>Hee that hath eares to heare, let him heare. Take heed how yee heare.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mar. 4.24. Jam. 1.19.</note> 
                     <hi>Be ſwift to heare,</hi> and the like.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                     <hi>Through intemperancie;</hi> When the ſtomacke is full, how can the eyes bee but heavy? Thereby the ſenſes are ſo op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, that during the ſame they cannot execute their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; and experience ſheweth that wee doe oftener and more readily ſleepe at Church in the afternoone, then in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone. Yea, if this ſhutteth
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:184293:32"/>out the Spirit, (according to that of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Eph. 5.18. 2 Pet. 2.5. Gen. 9.21. 2 Pet. 2.8.</note> 
                     <hi>and be not drunke with wine wherein is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, but be filled with the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi>) made <hi>Noah</hi> (a <hi>Preacher of righteouſneſſe</hi>) <hi>diſcover his nakedneſſe:</hi> occaſioned juſt <hi>Lot</hi> (who dwelling among the <hi>Sodomites,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 19.33, 34, &amp;c.</note> in <hi>ſeeing and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vexed his righteous ſoule from day to day with their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull deeds</hi>) in beaſtly man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to abuſe himſelfe (by fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy inceſt) with thoſe that came out of his owne loynes, and through the ſame the day of judgement ſhall take men at unawares (as is implied in that of our Saviour;<note place="margin">Luk. 21.34.</note> 
                     <hi>And take heed to your ſelves, leſt at any time your hearts bee over-charged with ſurfetting and drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and cares of this life, and ſo that day come upon you una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares.</hi>) How can it but in like manner occaſion this?<note place="margin">Ecclus. 31.20</note> 
                     <hi>Sound ſleep</hi> (ſaith the ſonne of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rach</hi>) <hi>commeth of moderate
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:184293:32"/>eating, but this</hi> for the moſt part of immoderate.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                     <hi>Through hatred of the Preacher,</hi> when wee cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide him, as <hi>Ahab</hi> could not indure <hi>Micaiah,</hi> when we are ſo affected towards him, as the <hi>Iewes</hi> towards <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> will wee attentively heare what he delivereth? Many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed (even thus affected) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford the Preacher their bodily preſence, but like images, <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving eyes, they ſee not,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 115.5.</note> 
                     <hi>having eares, they heare not;</hi> or if they afford them their eyes and eares it is to a ſiniſtrous end, even that they may have ſome ground or other from his cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, or from what hee delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to bring him into trouble and moleſtation.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
                     <hi>Through diſeſteeme of the Word read or preached.</hi> Too too many thinke that there is no more wiſdome therein, then their Teachers ſhew out of it, which in their conceit being
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:184293:33"/>very ſmall, or none at all, they neither watch thereat, nor thereunto. As no man cares for grace, but hee that knowes its worth; ſo none cares for the Word, but hee that hath it in high eſteeme for its unſpeakea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble excellencie. Thoſe prize it <hi>above thouſands of gold and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.72.78.148. Pſal. 19.10.</note> and unto them (as unto <hi>David,</hi> who <hi>meditated therein day and night</hi>) it is <hi>ſweeter then the honey and the honey combe.</hi> They that have drunke of this water of life, doe more and more thirſt after it, and (as <hi>Peter</hi> being informed how ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie it was that our Saviour ſhould waſh his feet, ſaid unto him,<note place="margin">Joh. 13.8, 9.</note> 
                     <hi>Lord, not my feet onely, but alſo my hands and my head</hi>) reſt not ſatisfied with ſipping or taſting hereof,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 23.15</note> but long as it were (as <hi>David</hi> to drinke of the water of the well of <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leem</hi> which is by the gate) even to be drunke therewith. Where this deſire is, there is watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:184293:33"/>where it is wanting, drowſineſſe.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
                     <hi>Through diſobedience un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the admonitions and reproofes of the Word,</hi> when being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed of our drowſineſſe, wee notwithſtanding doe not amend, but rather grow worſe and worſe, as the people in the dayes of <hi>Ieremie;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ier. 44.16.</note> As <hi>for the word which thou haſt ſpoken to us in the name of the Lord, wee will not hearken unto thee:</hi> When I ſay being againe and againe admoniſhed, wee not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding amend not, doe we not as it were through our obſtinacie, put out the light that wee may ſleepe the more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely?</p>
                  <p n="7">7. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 
                     <hi>Through ſhameleſnes.</hi> When we become ſo impudent, that though we be detected, noted, pointed at, ſpoken of, ſpoken againſt, ſpoken to, as common ſleepers at Church, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently contemners of the Word; yea, and certainly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:184293:34"/>that thereby we make our ſelves as gazing ſtocks, or common objects of laughter, yet having as it were an whores forehead, wee are not aſhamed, but doe the more goe on in the ſame. Of us may it be ſaid;<note place="margin">Iſa. 3 9.</note> 
                     <hi>The ſhew of their counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance doth witneſſe againſt them, and they declare their ſinne as Sodome, they hide it not;</hi> Yea, (as drowſie ſluggards which love to ſleep) how loath are we, how unwilling to be awaked? how froward? how angry when wee are awaked.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 
                     <hi>Through inconſideratneſſe,</hi> or <hi>want of conſideration,</hi> as well of the excellencie of the Word, and neceſſity of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſame, as of our owne proneneſſe unto drowſineſſe: Satans endeavours to lull us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepe, and our owne weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to reſiſt the ſame; Were wee affected with thoſe, wee could not but bee more watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:184293:34"/> 9. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> 
                     <hi>Through the want of Gods feare.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 20.11.</note> As <hi>Abraham</hi> unto <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bimelech</hi> (enquiring of him, why hee had ſaid of <hi>Sarah,</hi> that <hi>ſhee was his ſiſter) becauſe I thought, ſurely the feare of God is not in this place, and they will ſlay me for my wives ſake.</hi> So may wee of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepers, that wanting Gods feare, they will make no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of ſinne. Yea,<note place="margin">Pſal. 36.1, 2, 3, 4.</note> as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> layeth downe the want of Gods feare to be the ground of the ungodlies, ungodly both workes, words, and thoughts, ſo may wee noleſſe confidently affirme, that it is the ground of this wickedneſſe, and as <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 1.7.</note> 
                     <hi>The feare of the Lord is the beginning of knowledge,</hi> ſo wee,<note place="margin">Iudg. 16.20.</note> 
                     <hi>The want of it, is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this particular fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. Sampſon</hi> not being afraid of the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> ſlept to the deſtruction of his body, as too too many being voide of Gods feare ſleepe at Church, to the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:184293:35"/>deſtruction both of ſoule and body. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">10. <hi>Through cuſtome and willingneſſe.</hi> For when being come to Church, and no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſet, but wee ſet our ſelves to ſleepe (ſo with the dogge returning to our vomite) hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding downe our heads, and leaning them on our elbowes, as on pillowes, pulling our hats over our eyes leſt wee ſhould ſee (an unreverent thing in Gods houſe) and ſtopping our eares as it were, leſt the noiſe or voyce of the Preacher ſhould awake us, or hinder us from our ſleepe, doe not wee wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly bring the ſame upon us? and doth not this willingneſſe occaſion the ſame?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 3. <hi>Others.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Preachers.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">From Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1.</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                     <hi>When</hi> they doe not at any time, or upon any occaſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove this ſinne, or diſſwade
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:184293:35"/>their Auditors from the ſame.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2.</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                     <hi>When</hi> they take no paines in their miniſtrie, neither ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to any purpoſe, for what they doe deliver.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3.</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                     <hi>When</hi> they doe either preach their owne inventions,<note place="margin">Ezek, 22.28.</note> mens traditions, <hi>or</hi> lies and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours in the name of the Lord.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4.</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                     <hi>When</hi> they doe not ſute and fit their doctrine to the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie of their hearers.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5.</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
                     <hi>When</hi> they doe not what in them lyes to bring their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple unto a love and liking of the Word.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6.</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
                     <hi>When</hi> they continue too long in their Sermons.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7.</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 
                     <hi>When</hi> they lead a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous life, walke inordinatly, and their converſation is ſuch as becommeth not the Goſpel of Chriſt, <hi>like unto thoſe of whom the Prophet makes mention.</hi> His watchmen are blinde:<note place="margin">Iſa. 56.10.</note> they are all ignorant: they are all dumbe dogs, they cannot barke, ſleeping, lying downe, loving to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:184293:36"/>ſlumber, yea they are greedy dogges which can never have enough, and they are ſhepheards which cannot underſtand; they all looke to their owne way, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one for gaine from his quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp;c. <hi>and of whom the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle;</hi> All ſeeke their owne,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.21.</note> not the things which are Ieſus Christs.<note place="margin">Phil. 3.18.</note> 
                     <hi>And againe,</hi> many walke of whom I have told you often, and now tell you even weeping, that they are the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the croſſe of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Verſe. 19.</note> whoſe end is deſtruction, whoſe God is their belly, and whoſe glory is in their ſhame, who mind earthly things.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 2.17.</note> 
                     <hi>Through the ſinne of</hi> Eli <hi>his ſonnes</hi> men abhorred the ſacrifice of the Lord; <hi>So by reaſon of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of ſuch Paſtors, their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry becommeth odious and loathſome, and not a few (even of the beſt) ſleepe thereat.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>People,<note place="margin">From people through Commiſſion.</note> 
                     <hi>both by doing and leaving undone.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Doing, <hi>namely by</hi> giving
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:184293:36"/>themſelves over hereunto, <hi>whereby they become ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling-blocks unto others, invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them as it were to follow their courſe, and as readily to embrace ſleepe as themſelves doe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Leaving undone;<note place="margin">Omiſſion.</note> 
                     <hi>namely to</hi> awake thoſe, whom they ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be aſleepe. <hi>Hereby doe they wrong both themſelves and them that ſleepe; as who by letting them alone commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with them in their ſinne, and ſo ſhall bee puniſhed for their ſleeping, they themſelves in the meane time being awake.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:184293:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> Reaſons diſſwading from Church-ſleeping, they are of divers <hi>ſorts,</hi> and may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced into theſe <hi>eleven.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The 1. may be taken from <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 2. from <hi>The word of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 3. from <hi>The Preacher.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 4. from <hi>The Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 5.<note place="margin">Arguments againſt Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleeping from</note> from <hi>The place of mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 6. from <hi>The end of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 7. from <hi>The time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 8. from <hi>Satan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 9. from <hi>Our ſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 10. from <hi>Sleepe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 11. from <hi>Sleepers at Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:184293:37"/>
                  <head>Sect. 1. God: The
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Father.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sonne.</hi>
                           <note place="margin">God.</note>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In reſpect of his abſolute <hi>precept</hi> and <hi>command</hi> to attend, and give eare unto his Word; <hi>Heare inſtruction, and be wiſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 8.33. Eccleſ. 5.1.</note> 
                     <hi>and refuſe it not. Keepe thy foot when thou goeſt to the houſe of God, and be more ready to heare,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 11.15.</note> 
                     <hi>then to give the ſacrifice of fooles. Hee that hath eares to heare, let him heare,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iam. 1.19.</note> 
                     <hi>let eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man be ſwift to heare.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In reſpect of the gracious <hi>promiſes</hi> which hee hath made unto them which are hearers indeed.<note place="margin">Pro. 8.34. Pro. 15.31. Ioh. 5.24.</note> 
                     <hi>Bleſſed is the man that heareth me. The eare that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the reproofe of life abideth among the wiſe. Hee that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth my word, and beleeveth on him that ſent me, hath everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life, and ſhall not come into condemnation, but is paſſed. from death unto life.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.47.</note> 
                     <hi>He that is of God heareth Gods word.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:184293:38"/> 3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> In reſpect of his <hi>preſence</hi> about us, and with us, the knowledge which hee hath of us, and notice which hee taketh (though of us unperceived) whether wee wake or ſleepe.<note place="margin">Prov. 5.21.</note> 
                     <hi>The wayes of a man are before the eyes of the Lord</hi> (ſaith the wiſe man) <hi>and he pondereth all his paths;</hi> Yea, not his wayes alone (thoſe which are moſt conſpicuous) but the ſecret motions of the mind, and the inward intentions of his heart,<note place="margin">Heb. 4.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>they are all naked and opened</hi>) as the inwards of a beaſt that is cut up, and quarte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as the originall word ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth) <hi>unto the eyes of him, with whom we have to doe.</hi> And is God preſent in the Church ſo fearfull and glorious a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, of ſo ſharpe ſight, and deepe underſtanding, who dares ſleepe at Church?<note place="margin">Pro. 5.20.21</note> As hereby <hi>Salomon</hi> diſſwadeth from lewd and licentious cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,<note place="margin">Iob 34.23, 22</note> and hereby <hi>Elihu</hi> deterreth
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:184293:38"/>men from wicked practiſes, ſo by the ſame may wee be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawne from <hi>Church-ſleeping.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> In reſpect that <hi>it is God which ſpeaketh unto us in his Word.</hi> So thought the <hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Theſ. 2.13.</note> 
                     <hi>When yee received the word of God, which ye heard of us</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>yee received it not as the word of men, but (as it is in truth) the word of God, which effectually worketh alſo in you that beleeve.</hi> Would a ſubject ſleepe in the preſence of his Prince, adviſing him for his good threatening him for ſome evill committed by him: offering him prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the performance of this or that noble enterprize, and the like? hee would not. Care, feare, hope, joy, would keepe him awake. And will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſleepe, whilſt God offereth, promiſeth, rewardeth, threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teneth, inſtructeth, and the like?<note place="margin">1 Sam. 3.9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> When <hi>Samuel</hi> was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by <hi>Eli,</hi> that it was the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:184293:39"/>Lord which ſpake to him, ſleepe did then depart from his eyes; So ſhould not we ſleepe, if we would but perſwade our ſelves of Gods preſence.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> In reſpect of his <hi>power,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 15.4.</note> not onely to <hi>bleſſe</hi> his Word that it may bee profitable unto us,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.16.</note> for comfort, for doctrine, for reproofe, for correction, and for inſtruction in righteouſneſſe (whereof out of his love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, and willingneſſe to doe us good, hee is moſt deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and without whoſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, though <hi>Paul</hi> plant,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.6.</note> and <hi>Apollos</hi> water,) it bringeth not increaſe, but in <hi>juſtice,</hi> to inflict grievous judgements on them which doe not, or wil not heare, judgements I ſay, both corporall, as on <hi>Eutichus,</hi> and ſpirituall,<note place="margin">Act. 20.9.</note> as <hi>on the contemners of wiſdome, Prov.</hi> 1.24, 25, &amp;c. And thoſe obſtinate ones, of whom the Lord ſpeaketh to his Prophet;<note place="margin">Iſa. 6.10.</note> 
                     <hi>Make the heart of this people fat, and make their
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:184293:39"/>eares heavy, and ſhut their eyes, leſt they ſee with their eyes, and heare with their eares, and underſtand with their heart, and convert, and be healed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. 2.</hi> The Word of God.<note place="margin">The Word its</note>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In reſpect of <hi>its dignitie,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Dignity evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced by its</note> which is from the <hi>Author</hi> thereof: the <hi>Nature</hi> thereof: the <hi>Matter</hi> therein contained, together with the <hi>Antiquity</hi> and <hi>perpetuity</hi> of the ſame, may be cleerely evidenced.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Author</hi> thereof,<note place="margin">Author.</note> God, which is therefore tearmed <hi>Gods wayes:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 25.5. &amp; 29.9. &amp; 33.6. Iſa. 2.3. &amp; 26.19. Luk. 11.49. Heb. 4.12. Luk. 1.70.</note> 
                     <hi>the ſpeach of Gods glory: the breath of Gods mouth: Gods paths: the dew of the Lord: the wiſdome of God: the ſword of the Spirit.</hi> As hee ſpake of old <hi>by the mouth of his holy Prophets, which have beene ſince the world began;</hi> So doth hee now <hi>ſpeake</hi> by his <hi>Miniſters,</hi> whom
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:184293:40"/>as his <hi>Ambaſſadors,</hi> hee hath raiſed up in their roomes.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Nature</hi> thereof,<note place="margin">The nature thereof.</note> both as it is in it ſelfe, and as it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us.</p>
                  <p>As <hi>it is in it ſelfe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">As it is in it ſelfe. Pſal. 19.7. Pſa. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>9.160</note> it is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, eternall, immortall, moſt pure and precious. A moſt true, right, certaine, infallible, ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, faithfull, abſolute, ſincere, unſpotted, and undeniable Word, alwayes conſtant, one and the ſame for ever, wherein there is no errour, no falſhood; no defect, no imperfection.</p>
                  <p>As <hi>it is unto us.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">As it is unto us.</note> It is wine to comfort us; bread to feed us: drinke to quench ourthirſt: fire to purge us: an hammer to beate upon our hardned hearts: a ſtaffe to uphold us: a treaſure to inrich us: a lant horne to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect us: a guide to conduct us: a weapon to defend us: ſeed to beget us: meate for men: milke for babes. Yea, as the Sunne is to the world, ſo is it to us, the light of our lives, and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:184293:40"/>the life of our ſoules.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Matter</hi> therein contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,<note place="margin">The matter therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</note> ſuch as may give content unto all, the ſame ſo farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding all other ſubjects, as the Creator (whoſe workes and will it principally ſetteth forth) doth the creatures. It <hi>revealeth</hi> unto us the bleſſed <hi>Trinitie.</hi> It maketh knowne unto us <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and him <hi>cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi> It pointeth out unto us the <hi>vertue</hi> of his <hi>death</hi> and <hi>reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</hi> It ſetteth forth the <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies</hi> of a <hi>better life,</hi> which for the <hi>preſent</hi> are <hi>wholly</hi> hid from the <hi>ungodly,</hi> and but in <hi>part</hi> revealed unto the <hi>godly.</hi> Doth any loath it for its plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? It is <hi>milke for babes:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 11.10</note> It is <hi>pleaſant,</hi> affording unto each Chriſtian heart more ſweetneſſe then is in the honey, and the honey combe. It is <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right,</hi> as being voide of errour. It is <hi>a word of truth,</hi> pure wheat without chaffe: pure gold without droſſe. It is <hi>a
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:184293:41"/>word of wiſdome,</hi> whereby alone we become wiſe. It is <hi>as a goad,</hi> whereby being pricked, whilſt wee ſleepe in ſinne, wee doe thereupon awake. It is <hi>as a naile,</hi> whereby indeed wee are faſtened and confirmed. Is any delighted with <hi>hiſtory,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rener. Clivis Script.</note> 
                     <hi>prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, parables, lawes,</hi> morall, ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall, and Ceremoniall, <hi>Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphie, Coſmographie, Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomie, Arithmeticke, Logicke, Rhetoricke, Muſicke,</hi> and what ſoever elſe? Yea, who ſo lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth after <hi>newes,</hi> from heave aboue, from the earth beneath from the waters which are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the earth; <hi>Newes</hi> of <hi>wars peace, plenty, famine,</hi> and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> like. Hereby may hee in ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> receive ſatisfaction.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Antiquitie</hi> and <hi>perpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> tuitie</hi> thereof.<note place="margin">The Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and perpetuity thereof.</note> As it yet co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth, ſo hath it done, eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> from the very beginning, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> even the Word written is mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ancient, of greater antiquit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> then, all other writings now e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in the world.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:184293:41"/> 2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In reſpect of <hi>its neceſſitie,</hi> which may appeare by conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering;<note place="margin">Neceſſity, from</note> firſt the eſtate where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we are. 2. The eſtate where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we ſhould be. 3. The eſtate of ſuch as are altogether de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived thereof.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The eſtate wherein naturally wee are,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The eſtate wherein we are,</note> dead in treſpaſſes and ſinne; wanderers from God; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reyes unto the divell, poore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd blind, unregenerate: pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed with ſinne both in ſoule and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ody: ſtony-hearted; unfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ull and barren, guilty of death <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd damnation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hen needfull? a trumpet to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake us: a guide to conduct us: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> buckler to ſhield us: a treaſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o enrich us: eye-ſalve to anoint <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s: ſeed to beget us: a fountaine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o waſh us: raine, both to mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ifie us, and make us fruitfull.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The eſtate wherein we ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e,</hi> Alive unto God:<note place="margin">The eſtate wherein we ſhould be,</note> the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iers and ſervants of Chriſt: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>emples of the holy Ghoſt: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ruitfull in good workes, and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:184293:42"/>the like; and hereunto doe we attaine through Gods word.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>eſtate of ſuch as are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together deprived therof,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The eſtate of ſuch as are without it.</note> wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and miſerable. No judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment greater then famine, no famine ſo grievous, as this of the Word.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> In reſpect <hi>of its utilitie,</hi> which may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>appeare,<note place="margin">Amos 8.12. Its utility ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing by</note> 1. By the ſimilitudes whereby it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. 2. By the effects which are thereby produced. 3. By the duties which are thereto of us required. 4. By the meane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> which for the ſuppreſſing and hindering thereof have beene at all times by Satan and his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments uſed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The ſimilitudes whereby it is expreſſed</hi> are divers,<note place="margin">Similitudes.</note> as Manna, bread, water, light, a rod of ſtrength, wine, fire, ſilver, a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſtone, a new garment, a banner, a ſharp ſword, a glaſſe, a ſtaffe, &amp;c. This being no leſſe (or rather much more) profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for the ſoule then thoſe
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:184293:42"/>(and the like) for the body.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The effects which are thereby produced,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">effects.</note> are ſuch as concerne either this, or the life to come. <hi>This.</hi> It clenſeth us. It inligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teneth us. It regenerateth us. It changeth us. It makes us fruitfull. It maketh us wiſe to Salvation. It gladdeth our hearts with ſpirituall joy. It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>egetteth faith in us. Wee are hereby informed of the duties which wee owe one towards <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nother. It tells the Magiſtrate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ow hee ſhould rule, who elſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>night be either too ſevere, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oo milde.<note place="margin">Eraſ. apophth. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> milde. As <hi>Machetes</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed from <hi>Philip</hi> aſleepe (for whilſt his cauſe was pleading <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e was aſleepe) to <hi>Philip</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, ſo ſendeth it them from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heir ungodly government, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> that which is lawfull. It tels <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>udges,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 24.26.</note> that <hi>with Festus they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uſt not looke for bribes.</hi> It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ls <hi>Subjects,</hi> that with <hi>Sheba,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Sam. 20.21</note> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ey must not be rebellious.</hi> It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s <hi>husbands,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Col. 3.19.</note> that they <hi>must
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:184293:43"/>love their wives, and not be bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to them.</hi> It tells <hi>wives</hi> that they <hi>muſt not be taunting Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninnaes,</hi> painted <hi>Jezabels,</hi> who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh <hi>Dalilaes,</hi> ſcolding <hi>Zippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raes.</hi> It informes <hi>Miniſters</hi> to <hi>be inſtant</hi> (in preaching the Word) in <hi>ſeaſon,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.2.</note> 
                     <hi>and out of ſeaſon.</hi> It tells <hi>Lawyers,</hi> how and for whom they are to plead:<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.6.</note> It directs the <hi>Merchan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> and <hi>tradeſman,</hi> how to bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and ſell, &amp;c. Now if it wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not for the Word, would any of thoſe performe their duties <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nay,<note place="margin">Cic. de fato.</note> by it (as <hi>Socrates</hi> from hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> naturall conſtitution by the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Philoſophie) they an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> bettered both in their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and practiſe. Through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> doe the <hi>covetous</hi> forſake the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Mammon;</hi> the <hi>drunkard</hi> hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>wine;</hi> the <hi>adulterer</hi> his <hi>lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> which (till it thus worke) a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> unto them no leſſe preciou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> then their lives. Would <hi>Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> have heard <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Eli</hi> his ſonnes their Father, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:184293:43"/>might have learned their duty;<note place="margin">Rev. 16.15.</note> and eſcaped the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which befell them. By hearing this and watching hereat we are bleſſed;<note place="margin">Luk. 16.29. Mat. 26.41.</note> hereby are ſaved from hell, and hereby avoide temptations. If here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at we be informed of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of Gods enemies, ſhall we not hereupon profit the Church by calling upon God, in the words of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Awake,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 44.23.</note> 
                     <hi>why ſleepeſt thou O Lord? ariſe, cast us not off for ever.</hi> And as when <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> could not ſleepe,<note place="margin">Eſter 6.3.</note> hee had his <hi>Chronicles</hi> brought unto him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon came to know what <hi>Mordecay</hi> had done for him, ſo if wee would awake at the reading and preaching of the Word, we ſhould heare what deliverance the Lord hath wrought for our poore ſoules. <hi>The life to come.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joh. 12.48.</note> The <hi>Word must judge us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Duties required of us.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The duties required of us in reſpect of it. Prov. 3.3. Prov. 7.2. Col. 3.16: Iam. 1.19.21</note> 
                     <hi>To write it in the tables of our
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:184293:44"/>heart. To keepe it as the apple of our eye. To let it dwell in us plenteouſly. To bee ſwift to heare. To have it ingrafted in us, and receive it with meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;</hi> Yea, not onely to be <hi>hearers,</hi> but <hi>doers</hi> thereof, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing it above Rubies, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting it ſweeter then the honey and the honey combe, even as the words of eternall life. <hi>The oppoſition which by Satan and his inſtruments hath beene made againſt the ſame from time to time.</hi> Some have beene brought to diſlike it, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers not to believe it, others to fall from the hearing of it, others to deprave it, by mang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, mingling, perverting and miſapplying the ſame. Others to prohibite the reading and hearing thereof, and divers the like, which might particularly be inſtanced Every of which implieth the utilitie of the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:184293:44"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. 3.</hi> The Preacher.<note place="margin">The Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Becauſe at his peoples ſleeping hee cannot chooſe but be much <hi>diſcouraged.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Becauſe hereby he cannot but be much <hi>diſturbed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Becauſe ſuch cariage ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth their <hi>contempt</hi> of him.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Becauſe thus hee ſhould <hi>loſe</hi> his <hi>paines,</hi> as if one ſhould <hi>preach</hi> to a <hi>deafe</hi> man, or <hi>waſh</hi> an <hi>Aethiopian.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Becauſe hee is in <hi>Gods ſteed,</hi> as his <hi>ambaſſador,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.20.</note> and who bringeth the <hi>glad tydings of ſalvation,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 10.15.</note> whom if we ſhall not heare, we heare not Chriſt himſelfe, they being <hi>Wiſdomes</hi> his <hi>maidens.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. 4.</hi> The Congregation.<note place="margin">The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Becauſe the <hi>beſt</hi> are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>offended,</hi> and their <hi>attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n</hi> hindered.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Becauſe hereupon the <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant</hi>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:184293:45"/>either come not to Church, or if they come, ſleight the Word, as not worth the hearing. Yea, as thoſe which did eat in <hi>Idols</hi> temples,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 8.9.</note> occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned others alſo there to eate by their example, and as the very ſight of thoſe that yawne, is wont to ſet others on yaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; ſo the very ſight of others ſleeping, may make a man ſleepie, that were otherwiſe wakefull, much more ſhall one ſlothfull man infect another, and the rather, becauſe wee are prone enough of our ſelves to take infection without helpe, our inbred and inward corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being as flaxe, eaſie enough by the leaſt ſparkle to bee ſet on fire.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. 5.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The place of meeting.</note> The place of meeting.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> It is <hi>Bethel,</hi> Gods houſe As <hi>Jacob</hi> when hee had the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the ladder,<note place="margin">Gen. 28.17.</note> could ſay <hi>how dreadfull is this place
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:184293:45"/>This is none other but the houſe of God; and this is the gate of heaven.</hi> So (the Lord being here preſent in his owne ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances) are we to conceive of this.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It is as <hi>Betheſda,</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> where the blind, lame, paralyticke,<note place="margin">Joh. 5.3.</note> and ſuch other ſoule-diſeaſed crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures may have comfort; and are not wee ſuch? Wee thinke wee ſee, but wee are indeed blind; thinke wee know, but doe not indeed underſtand.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> It is a <hi>ſtore-houſe</hi> of all needfull <hi>commodities.</hi> Here are Gods <hi>ſtewards,</hi> his <hi>almners,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jſa. 55.1.</note> his <hi>Phyſitians?</hi> lackeſt thou meat, drinke, money, raiment, or whatſoever elſe? here is for thee. <hi>Ho! every one that thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth, come; and who ſo hunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, come, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. It is as <hi>Athens,</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> where <hi>newes</hi> were to bee <hi>heard;</hi> and <hi>Epheſus</hi> where <hi>ſhewes</hi> were to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e <hi>ſeene.</hi> What newes?<note place="margin">Iſa. 9.6.</note> that <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nto us a child is borne;</hi> that
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:184293:46"/>
                     <hi>hee is the propitiation for our ſinnes;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.18.</note> that <hi>God is reconciled unto us through Christ, &amp;c.</hi> What <hi>ſhowes?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.5.</note> 
                     <hi>God reſiſting the proud, but giving grace un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the humble. God breaking the hornes of the ungodly.</hi> Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>David,</hi> vanquiſhing great <hi>Goliah,</hi> with ſtore both of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies</hi> and <hi>Tragedies.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. 6.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The end of comming.</note> The end of comming.</head>
                  <p>Not to gaze, laugh, chide, prate, neither yet to ſleepe, as once one who had not ſlept wel the night before, and in the morning hearing the bell toll to Church, willed her maid to make ready, <hi>for ſhee would goe to Church to take a nap,</hi> but to heare,<note place="margin">Luk. 21.38. &amp; 22.46.</note> pray, and ſing, and why then wilt thou ſleepe? Tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> muſt rouſe up thy ſelfe, til<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> which time thou muſt ofte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> heare, <hi>riſe and pray,</hi> and <hi>heare</hi> and <hi>ſing.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:184293:46"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. 7.</hi> The Time.<note place="margin">The Time.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                     <hi>It is time now to awake.</hi> As when the Sunne ſhines wee are to make hay,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.11.</note> and wee muſt ſtrike whilſt the iron is hot. The <hi>Piſmire followes her buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the Summer,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 10.5.</note> 
                     <hi>and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth meat for Winter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                     <hi>It is Gods harveſt; Now he that ſleepeth in harvest is a ſonne that cauſeth ſhame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3"> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. <hi>They that ſleepe, ſleepe in the night,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.5.</note> 
                     <hi>and the night com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth wherein no man can worke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                     <hi>The time is but ſhort, could yee not watch with mee one houre?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 24.42.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
                     <hi>Wee muſt give an account for the ſame;</hi> and at what houre wee ſhall bee called to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count wee know not. It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of us to <hi>number our dayes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 90.12.</note> which aſſuredly <hi>whilſt we ſleepe</hi> we cannot doe.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
                     <hi>No time but ſhould be well
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:184293:47"/>ſpent;</hi> how much more this? <hi>Titus</hi> conceived that he had loſt that day,<note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt of the Church.</note> wherein hee had not done ſome good, and ſo doſt thou the profit which commeth of the Word, by ſleeping thereat.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 8.<note place="margin">Satan.</note> 
                     <hi>Satan.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> He and our other enemies, the world without,<note place="margin">Iſa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.27.</note> and the fleſh within (as <hi>Iſraels</hi> ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies) ſleepe not. <hi>Philip</hi> ſaid, <hi>he might ſafely ſleepe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eraſ. apophth.</note> 
                     <hi>for An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipater was awake;</hi> but we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily, <hi>muſt awake, for the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell</hi> (an Anti-pater indeed) <hi>is not aſleepe.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.8.</note> 
                     <hi>Bee ſober and watch</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>for your adverſary the divell, goeth about continually, like a roaring lyon, ſeeking whom he may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure. Shall men watch</hi> (ſaith the heathen man) <hi>to ſlay and deſtroy others,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Vt jugulent homines, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Horat. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>and wilt not thou watch to ſave thy ſelfe?</hi> So ſay I, ſhall Satan bee more vigilant to doe us a ſhrewd turne, or a
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:184293:47"/>miſchiefe, then we in watching to keepe our ſelves ſafe from his malice?<note place="margin">Simile:</note> Thoſe that would tame Deere, keepe them from ſleepe, but the divell to make us wilde, ſets us to ſleepe. As hee watcheth continually to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault us, eſpecially when wee are at Church, wee muſt then eſpecially awake to reſiſt him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Not any thing doth hee more endevour to hinder, then our hearing the Word, as who knoweth well, what harme would enſue, if he could here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in prevaile, even that grace ſhould decreaſe, and ſinne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe. This doth hee labour both by himſelfe and by his inſtruments.<note place="margin">Mar. 3.24.</note> 
                     <hi>As a kingdome divided cannot ſtand;</hi> So could he divide us from the Word, we were undone.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> He is <hi>a theefe;</hi> The <hi>Scribes and Phariſees ſet a watch,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 27.66.</note> 
                     <hi>leſt Chriſt ſhould be ſtollen,</hi> and ſo muſt we, leſt being aſleepe all goodneſſe bee taken from us:
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:184293:48"/>and as the Souldiers, of Chriſt, though untruly,<note place="margin">Mat. 28.13.15.</note> 
                     <hi>whilſt we ſlept his diſciples came and ſtole him away.</hi> Wee may ſay truly, whilſt we have ſlept, the divell came and deprived us of much good;<note place="margin">Iudg. 16.20.</note> yea, as whilſt <hi>Sampſon</hi> was aſleepe his ſtrength was gone, which to his unſpeakable miſery he quickly felt being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, ſo through thy Church-ſleeping haſt thou not experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally found decay of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſtrength?</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The divell is the <hi>envious man,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 13.25.</note> who ſoweth tares whilſt we are aſleepe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. 9.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Our ſelves.</note> Our ſelves.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                     <hi>Our Religion and honeſtie will be called into queſtion;</hi> yea, hereupon ſhal we be ſuſpected (and that not without cauſe) that wee did ſpend the night before in riot, wantonneſſe, or doing ſome other miſchiefe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                     <hi>Our profeſſion.</hi> Wee <hi>are of the day,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.5.6.</note> and <hi>they that ſleepe, ſleepe in the night.</hi> In this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:184293:48"/>as unto <hi>Peter,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mar. 14.37.</note> 
                     <hi>Simon ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt thou?</hi> So may it bee unto us.<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> It is unſeemly that the Sun ſhould at any time find us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepe, but much more at Church.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                     <hi>The thankefulneſſe which we owe unto God for our bodily reſt.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.16: Prov. 3.28. Iob 7.4.14.</note> God gives us quiet reſt and ſleepe (whereas others haply have it but ſeldome, and therein are much terrified by dreames) and ſhould wee not then employ on God the whole man, when wee come to his houſe.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                     <hi>The uncertainty of our death.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 24.42.</note> 
                     <hi>Watch therefore</hi> (ſaith our Saviour againe and againe) <hi>for you know not in what houre your maſter will come.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.7.</note> So <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, The end of all things is at hand, bee ſober therefore and watch unto prayer.</hi> Though we be neither weake, nor ſicke, nor old, yet may death ſeize on us, and our Sunne may even ſet at noone. How many have
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:184293:49"/>riſen well in the morning that never went to bed againe? Some have died whilſt they were a preaching the Word; Some in hearing the ſame; why may not others in ſleeping thereat? and that in juſtice, but who would willingly ſo die? Didſt thou thinke that when thou ſetteſt thy ſelfe to ſleepe at Church, thou ſhouldſt never ſleep more, thou ſhouldſt die upon the doing thereof, and be preſently called to give an account, and make anſwer to God for it, wouldſt thou ſo doe? wouldſt thou that <hi>thy maſter ſhould find thee thus doing?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 13:36.</note> thou wouldſt not. If thou lookſt not to it, who can tell but that thou maiſt be taken away in this act of iniquitie? oh that they were wiſe,<note place="margin">Dent. 32:29.</note> that they underſtood this, that they would conſider their latter end!</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
                     <hi>Our ignorance in points of Chriſtianity,</hi> and of ſuch things
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:184293:49"/>as tend unto our ſoules ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.20.</note> How few are there which are indeed men and women of knowledge, or rather are not children in underſtanding? unto how many is not the Scripture, as a booke ſealed up?<note place="margin">Iſa. 29.11.</note> who is able to tell the meaning almoſt of any place of Scripture? how many take ſuch things li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terally, which are to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood figuratively, and ſuch things figuratively, which are literally to be taken? where is the fault? when by the Word they might receive inſtruction, and <hi>wiſdomes maidens</hi> are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering them underſtanding,<note place="margin">Prov. 9.4.</note> they are aſleepe.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>Wee watch about our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Non princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pem ſolidam dormire no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctem. Eraſ. chil. Luc. <hi>2.8.</hi>
                     </note> and in reſpect of tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall buſineſſes, Captaines, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners, Souldiers, Shepheards, &amp;c. watch in their places, and ſervants muſt not ſleepe when their Maſters ſpeake to them.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. <hi>Wee would bee angry,</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> if when <hi>wee ſpeake, other would
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:184293:50"/>not heare us, or ſleepe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 
                     <hi>Wee can wake, if a tale be told us.</hi> Wee ſleepe not, when we are informed of our world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly buſineſſes, we ſleepe not, if one tell us of ſome great eſtate befallen us, or ſome great good procured for us, as pardon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rebels, riches being poore, happineſſe being miſerable, and the like; every of which the Scripture revealeth unto us.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> 
                     <hi>Our care to doe good.</hi> The wicked ſleepe not before they have done ſome miſchiefe,<note place="margin">Prov. 4.16.</note> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there ſhould we before we have done ſome good, which wee doe not,<note place="margin">Act. 16.14.</note> if with <hi>Lydia,</hi> wee at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not on the things deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 10.<note place="margin">Sleepe.</note> 
                     <hi>Sleepe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jt is a Publican,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Quantum ad debitum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinui profectus, nibit ita de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perit de vita noſtra, qudm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quod ſomno deputatur. Bernard.</note> A Culler, or rather devourer of time, it neither doth any part of time Waſte to leſſe purpoſe, then
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:184293:50"/>that which is ſpent in ſleepe, and what then is to bee thought of that, which is ſpent in ſleepe at Church?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 11. <hi>Sleepers.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Sleepers.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                     <hi>Such as are given hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to are of bad report.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.5.6</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                     <hi>Such as will not hearken are given over.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 81.11.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                     <hi>Their prayer is abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pro. 28.9.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                     <hi>Doing the worke of the Lord negligently they are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ier: 48.10.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
                     <hi>They are in danger of Gods judgements,</hi> and ſo continuing ſhall not eſcape them. What befell <hi>Noah, Siſera, Sampſon,</hi> being aſleepe, who knoweth not? Theirs might bee lawfull after a ſort, yet were then met withall, but how much more this, being wholly unlawfull? The <hi>mother</hi> being <hi>aſleepe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 King. 3.20.</note> had her <hi>live child</hi> taken away, and a <hi>dead child</hi> put in the <hi>roome;</hi>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:184293:51"/>If thou beeſt not watchfull, in ſtead of a living, thou maiſt bee poſſeſſed of a dead heart. As the <hi>Diſciples</hi> unto <hi>Christ</hi> being aſleepe,<note place="margin">Luk. 8.24.</note> 
                     <hi>Maſter wee periſh;</hi> ſo may it unto us thus ſleeping, if thou doeſt not awake, thou periſheſt, there being prepared (as once one which crying <hi>fire, fire,</hi> and being demanded where, anſwered <hi>in hell for ſleepers at Church.</hi>) Prepared (I ſay) for ſuch, fearefull judgements.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
                     <hi>They are for the preſent as dead.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 
                     <hi>They are as Images,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving eares,<note place="margin">Pſal. 115.5.</note> but not hearing therewith.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 
                     <hi>They loſe the comfort</hi> or <hi>admonition</hi> intended for them.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> 
                     <hi>They ſhall be cloathed with rags.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pro. 23.21. Pro. 20.18.</note> As <hi>hee that loveth ſleepe commeth to poverty;</hi> So he that loveth to ſleepe at Church can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but bee poore in grace, and ſeeing <hi>the abundance of the rich will not ſuffer him to ſleepe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.12.</note> thy
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:184293:51"/>ſleepe bewrayes thy povertie.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. <hi>They receive no benefit by the Word preached,</hi> the ſame being unto them wholly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Objections for Church-ſleeping anſwered.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hey are of divers <hi>ſorts,</hi> (ſome juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying it, others ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuating it, others tranſlating the fault thereof on others) all which may bee reduced into theſe five;
<list>
                     <item>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Objections. </seg>
                        </label> Whereof the 1. may be taken from <hi>The ſinne it ſelfe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The 2. from <hi>The perſon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting it.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The 3. from <hi>The Preacher.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The 4. from <hi>The matter delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The 5. <hi>The perſons reproving it.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:184293:52"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. 1.</hi> The ſinne it ſelfe.<note place="margin">From the ſin itſelfe.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">I. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> 
                     <hi>It is no great ſinne.</hi> It is at the moſt but one of the little ones,<note place="margin">A.</note> and ſo not worth the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding. A. 1. If it bee a ſinne, it is to be avoided, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> how ſmall ſoever in it ſelfe? How ſmall ſoever in compariſon of other ſinnes.<note place="margin">Ier. 4.14. Iſa. 3.16.</note> The Lord taketh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice even of vaine <hi>thoughts,</hi> diſdainfull and proud <hi>lookes,</hi> wanton <hi>eyes,</hi> walking with ſtretched-forth <hi>necks,</hi> and ſuch other unſeemly <hi>geſtures,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 12.36.</note> and <hi>of every idle word that men ſhall ſpeake, they ſhall give an account on the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> how much more then taketh he notice of this ſinne? How much more ſhall wee be called to an account for the ſame? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                     <note place="margin">Gutta cavat lapidem non vi, ſed ſaepè <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>adendo.</note> 2. Even ſmall ſinnes continued in, and unrepented of, becomming at the length ſinnes of cuſtomeare moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous. A drop of water by
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:184293:52"/>falling on the hardeſt ſtone ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it at the length hollow, and the ſmalleſt ſinne continued in, doth at the length no leſſe wound the conſcience then the greateſt; yea, <hi>thoſe which at the length prove hainous crimes, were but</hi> (as we may ſo ſpeake) <hi>pettie offences.</hi> Did not Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners daily pumpe out the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that by little and little (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perceived) entereth the ſhip, it would be thereby no leſſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered, then by ſome ſudden great leake; ſo did not Gods children daily mortifie their ſmalleſt corruptions, they could not but at one time or other, make ſhipwracke of Faith and of a good conſcience. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. It is even in it ſelfe a great ſinne, and in like manner the cauſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as hath beene already ſhewed. 4. Gods children make conſcience even of their ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt ſinnes.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 24.5.</note> If <hi>David</hi> doe but but off the lappe of <hi>Sauls</hi> gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, his heart ſmites him for
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:184293:53"/>it.<note place="margin">Exod. 10.26.</note> As <hi>Moſes</hi> would have the cattell to goe with them, and not an hoofe to bee left behind for <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> that thereof they might take to ſerve the Lord their God in the wilderneſſe, ſo muſt not we employ any one member on the ſervice of Satan,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.1.</note> but our whole man in every part and facultie thereof on the ſervice of God at all times. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 5. Even for ſmall ſinnes (as wee may ſo ſpeake) hath God inflicted fearefull judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,<note place="margin">Gen. 20.2. 6.18.</note> as on the familie of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bimelech,</hi> who had taken (but not touched) <hi>Sarai Abrahams</hi> wife:<note place="margin">1 Sam. 6.19. 2 Sam. 6.7.</note> On the men of <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhemeſh</hi> for looking into the Arke, and on <hi>Vzza</hi> for putting his hand thereon, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> when the oxen ſhaked it. 6. As the leaſt ſinne diſpleaſeth God, and for the leaſt wee are to call upon God for mercy (as <hi>David</hi> for the ſinnes of his youth) ſo ever the leaſt occaſioned the death of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Pſal: 1.25.7.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:184293:53"/> II. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> 
                     <hi>Jt is an ordinary uſuall thing,</hi> and ſo the leſſe to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded.<note place="margin">A.</note> A. Therefore it is the more dangerous, the more to be avoided,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.20:</note> Gods judgements being chiefly inflicted becauſe of Nationall ſinnes. Was not diſobedience the common ſinne of the old world? yet was not it left unpuniſhed.<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.5.</note> 
                     <hi>God ſpared not the old world</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>) <hi>but ſaved Noah the eight perſon a Preacher of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, bringing in the flood upon the world of the ungodly,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ezek. 16.49.</note> were not pride, fulneſſe of bread, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of idleneſſe, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifulneſſe to the poore the common ſinnes of <hi>Sodome?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.6.</note> 
                     <hi>yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>urned he it into aſhes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>emned it with an overthrow.</hi> Agreeable hereunto is that of he Prophet touching <hi>Iſrael;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Hoſ. 411.</note> 
                     <hi>The Lord hath a controverſie with the inhabitants of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>and, becauſe there is no truth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>or mercy, nor knowledge of God in the land.</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>2</label> 
                     <hi>By ſwearing
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:184293:54"/>and lying, and killing, and ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and committing of adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, they breake out, and blood toucheth blood. Therefore ſhall the land mourne,</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>3</label> 
                     <hi>and every one that dwelleth therein ſhall lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh.</hi> The <hi>Benjamites</hi> (one and all) tooke part with thoſe wicked men in <hi>Gibeah,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iudg. 20.14.</note> and did they not (notwithſtanding) ſmart for it? Though then Church-ſleeping bee common, it followeth not, that therefore it is warrantable. The rifer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny evill is in the places or ages we live in, the more carefull ſhould wee be to ſhun and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voide the ſame. <hi>See then</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that yee walke circumſpectly,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eph. 5.15, 16</note> 
                     <hi>not as fooles, but as wiſe, redeeming the time becauſe the dayes are evill.</hi> Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the times then wee live in, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the places wee abide in mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> then ordinarily evill in thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> kind? That giveth us no liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but ſhould make ſo much the more wary, leſt wee b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:184293:54"/>taken napping.<note place="margin">Gen. 6.9.</note> 
                     <hi>Noah was a juſt man in his generation,</hi> even in that generation, wherein the whole world was over-grown with wickedneſſe; ſo ſhould wee watch at Church, though others be thereat taken with the ſleeping evill.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> 
                     <hi>To ſleepe at Church is not hurtfull or prejudiciall unto others.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A.</note> 
                     <hi>A.</hi> But what good is there hereby done unto any?<note place="margin">Malum eſt non feciſſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, Chryſ. de virt. &amp; vit.</note> 
                     <hi>To doe no good, is in effect, the ſame with to doe evill;</hi> yea, thus doing, thou doſt both hurt thy ſelfe and others. Thy ſelfe as being hereby deprived of the ſincere milke of the Word. Others, as being unto them through thy evill example, a ſtone of offence.</p>
                  <p n="4">IIII. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IIII"/> 
                     <hi>To ſleepe at Church is not ſo bad, as then and there to have thoughts of covetouſneſſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ezek. 33.31.</note> 
                     <hi>eyes of adultery, revenge, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, and the like by being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake.</hi> A. 1.<note place="margin">A.</note> The queſtion is not, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> which of the two are the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:184293:55"/>leſſer evill, this, or that. 2. If thou didſt ſeriouſly conſider in whoſe preſence thou art, (even in his who is a God cloathed with majeſtie and honour,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.29.</note> a conſuming fire, and an everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting burning, who cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with ſinne (the leaſt ſinne) in any) and to what end thou didſt come into Gods houſe, thou wouldſt neither ſinne, ſo nor ſo. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. Thy thoughts and lookes being ſuch, it appeares that thou makeſt but ſmall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of thy wayes. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. If thou wouldſt pray with the Pſalmiſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.36.</note> 
                     <hi>Jncline mine heart unto thy Teſtimonies, and not to covetouſneſſe.</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>37</label> And, <hi>Turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way mine eyes from beholding vanity, and quicken thou me in thy way,</hi> thou ſhouldſt have no ſuch cauſe to object.</p>
                  <p n="5">V. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> 
                     <hi>It is not done of ſet purpoſe. A.</hi> Of ſet purpoſe leave it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done.<note place="margin">A.</note> Let it be thy ſtedfaſtreſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution whilſt thou art at Church, not to give ſleepe to
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:184293:55"/>thine eyes, norſlumber to rhine eye lids.</p>
                  <p n="6">VI. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> 
                     <hi>Sleepe there is but nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping;</hi> a ſmall time, a ſhutting of the eyes, a winke and away. A. Yet ſo that thou there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by loſeſt the whole Sermon.<note place="margin">A.</note> Though thou heareſt the Word now and then, yet how it han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth on the former, how it precedeth the latter, thou canſt not tell.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. 2.</hi> The perſons commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it.<note place="margin">The perſons committing it.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">I. <hi>I am accuſtomed hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> 
                     <hi>that either J muſt ſtay at home,</hi> or (notwithſtanding of mine unwillingneſſe to ſleepe, and paines which I take to ſhake it off) <hi>ſleepe, when I come to Church.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A.</note> A. 1. Though thou cuſtomarily ſleepeſt at Church, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> yet come, for haply (as Maſter <hi>Latimer</hi> once ſaid) <hi>thou maist be there taken napping.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Latimers</hi> Serm.</note> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. If thou diſlikeſt it, art humbled for
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:184293:56"/>it, and ſtriveſt againſt it, it is not thy ſinne, neither ſhall it be laid unto thy charge. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. If thou findeſt thy ſelfe prone thereunto, it is the ſinne that God eſpecially calleth thee to keepe watch and ward a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> 
                     <hi>I am old and weake, and ſo am to bee borne withall.</hi> Whatſoever it is in others, in me I hope it is no great ſinne to ſleepe at Church.<note place="margin">A.</note> A. 1. The older thou art, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the more need haſt thou to abſtaine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from, as being nigh thine end. 2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Thou wouldeſt be loath, that whilſt thou art thus ſleeping death ſhould ſeize on thee. 3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> As old as thou art, thou canſt watch longer about thine owne buſineſſe, or in hearing ſome vaine, triviall, ſinfull diſcourſe, or in ſeeing a Play, or ſome vaine ſhow. Canſt thou thus watch, and not watch one houre in hearing Gods Word? 4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                     <hi>Simeon</hi> was as old as thou
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:184293:56"/>art, yet when he came into the Temple,<note place="margin">Luk. 2.28.</note> did hee not thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have himſelfe, and <hi>Anna</hi> the Propheteſſe, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>36</label> 
                     <hi>who was a widow about foureſcore yeares depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not from the temple,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>but ſerved God with faſtings and prayers, night and day:</hi> yea, and <hi>Nicodemus</hi> to enjoy Chriſts company came by night unto him, when hee ſhould have ſlept.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> 
                     <hi>I watch on the other dayes of the weeke,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A.</note> 
                     <hi>and labour hardly.</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> A. 1. Thou wert then in thy calling for the good of thy body: and therefore didſt watch, and when thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt to Church thou art then alſo in thy calling for the good of thy ſoule, and therefore ſhouldſt watch. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Thou haſt watched indeed,<note place="margin">Eraſ. apophth. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> but was it for thy neighbours good (as <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menio</hi> excuſed <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon</hi> unto the <hi>Grecians</hi> which complained one time that hee ſleept by day, <hi>wonder not</hi> (ſaith
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:184293:57"/>he) <hi>that Philip now ſleepeth, for when yee ſlept</hi> (and ſeemed careleſſe of your owne affaires) <hi>hee was awake</hi>) was it not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for his good, or to worke him ſome miſchiefe?<note place="margin">Iob 24.14, 15, 16, 17.</note> 
                     <hi>The murtherer riſing with the light</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iob</hi>) <hi>killeth the poore, and needy,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for the morning is to them, even as the ſhadow of death.</hi> To the ſame purpoſe is that of the <hi>Poet,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Horat.</note> 
                     <hi>Theeves riſe by night, that they may ſlay men,</hi> as hath beene already al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged. If thou haſt thus wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched unto villany, whilſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were at their reſt, thou ſhalt find one day, that better it had beene for thee, that thou hadſt beene aſleepe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. If thou haſt done thine owne workes on the other dayes, thou muſt doe Gods on his. Since he hath not deprived thee of thy due (which notwithſtanding is onely thine by his gift) thou muſt not rob him of his. 4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Thou muſt not ſo toile on
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:184293:57"/>the weeke-dayes as thereby to make thy ſelfe unfit for the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying of the Lords day. 5. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Even by night are wee to watch in Gods ſervice,<note place="margin">Pſal. 134.1. Pſal. 119.55.</note> much more then by day, and on Gods day.</p>
                  <p n="4">IIII. <hi>I roſe very early.</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IIII"/> A. 1.<note place="margin">A.</note> Didſt thou not riſe about thine owne worldly affaires, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and art thereby made unfit for this duty? was it not to meet ſuch a friend, in ſuch a place, to bee merry with him for an houre or two before Sermon? was it not to make up ſuch and ſuch a bargaine formerly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of? was it not to caſt up thy accompts, and looke after thy Debtors? If thou didſt riſe for theſe or the like ends, better it had beene for thee to have lyen a bed. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. If thou ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt not for thoſe or the like ends, thou hadſt the more time to prepare thy ſelfe in private, for the performance of thy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in publike, neither would
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:184293:58"/>that have beene any let unto this, nay rather, prayer, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, meditation, and confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence preceding it, would bee eſpeciall furtherances there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
                  <p n="5">V. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> 
                     <hi>I have farre to Church, ſit farre from the pulpit, am thicke of hearing, and the Preachers voyce is weake.</hi> A.<note place="margin">A.</note> Though thou canſt not doe as thou wouldeſt, doe ſo much as thou canſt. Riſe earlier, and come ſooner, and ſit or ſtand nigher, waiting on Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, who as he hath given thee eares (and both can and hath made the deafe to heare) ſo may be pleaſed to beſtow on them their proper office of hearing;<note place="margin">Mar. 7.37.</note> yea, though thou canſt not heare, and ſo profi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thy ſelfe, yet thou muſt not ſleepe leſt thou offend others which may and would heare.</p>
                  <p n="6">VI. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> 
                     <hi>I know my duty alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as well as they that give beſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> attention.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A.</note> A. Suppoſe thou
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:184293:58"/>doeſt, yet ſhouldeſt thou know it much better by thy watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, neither doth the Word onely teach thee to know Gods will, but calleth upon thee to be a doer thereof.<note place="margin">Iam. 1.22.</note> 
                     <hi>Bee yee doers</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Iames</hi>) <hi>and not hearers onely.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">VII. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VII"/> 
                     <hi>What I ſhall loſe at one time by ſleeping at Church, I can get up, either when J come home, or at another time when I goe to Church. At home, either by reading as good a Sermon, or one on the ſame ſubject, if not the very ſame words, or by hearing the ſame repeated by ſome one in my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily which writeth the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. At Church, by giving attendance, unto what ſhall bee then and there delivered.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A.</note> A. To the firſt branch of the former,<note place="margin">To the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> branch there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Mal. 2.7.</note> 1. Experience teacheth that the lively voyce is more effectuall then ocular reading. 2. As <hi>the Prieſts lips are to preſerve knowledge;</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> So art thou requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:184293:59"/>
                     <hi>to heare it at his mouth.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mal. 2.7. &amp;c.</note> 3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> If thou canſt ſo well profit at home, why doſt thou come to Church at all? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4 Sermons are not therefore printed, that thou mighteſt heare no more, but to put thee in mind of what thou haſt already heard. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Thou art to profit as well by the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon which thou heareſt, as thoſe which thou readeſt. To the ſecond branch.<note place="margin">The ſecond branch.</note> 1. Doth hee ſo write it as that hee neither addeth thereto, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> nor taketh ther-from? I ſuppoſe few or none have ſuch cunning. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. No hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer can deliver it with that force and efficacie that the Preacher doth. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. If thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt no conſcience of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like hearing of it, much leſſe wilt thou to heare it privatly repeated, how exactly ſoever written. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. As the divell hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered thee from that, ſo will he from the performance of this duty.<note place="margin">To the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> To the latter. 1. That thou ſinneſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> if thou doeſt at all
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:184293:59"/>ſleepe at Church. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Thou maiſt give ſuch offence at one time, that thou canſt not ſalve it at another. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. May not God juſtly give thee over, that thou ſhalt not repent thereof, nor bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed there-from? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou the contrary, but that death may then ſeaze upon thee, and ſo how miſerable were thy condition?</p>
                  <p n="8">VIII. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VIII"/> 
                     <hi>Even the preciſeſt ſleepe at Church.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A.</note> A. 1. It is none of their vertues, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> neither are they herein to be imitated. 2. They doe as much as in them lyes ſtrive againſt it, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and are no doubt humbled for it. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. It is not ordinary with them, but occaſionally enforced. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. Others ſhould hereupon bee ſo farre from being emboldened or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged hereunto, as that they are to be ſo much the more wary in avoiding the ſame. 5. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Herein they differ from thee, Thou at Church ſeekeſt ſleepe, but their ſleepe findeth
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:184293:60"/>them. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 6. Thou there ſleepeſt quietly, but ſo unquiet is theirs, that even whilſt they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepe, they may be ſaid in ſome ſort to bee awake. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 7. Too too many which are or would bee reputed for ſuch, are farre e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough from being ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. 3.</hi> The Preacher.<note place="margin">The Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">I. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> 
                     <hi>Hee is no ſcholler; Hee is not read in humane Writers. Hee is no Logician, Hiſtorian, linguiſt. He is not acquainted with the Schoole-men. He ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not the Teſtimonies of the Fathers, and Doctors of the Church.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A.</note> A. 1. How knoweſt thou that hee is no ſcholler? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> becauſe hee uſeth no Latine, Greeke, or Hebrew. But ſhould he uſe <hi>Welch</hi> in ſtead of any of thoſe, wert thou able to detect him? nay, rather wouldſt thou not applaud his learning? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Cannot a Shoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:184293:60"/>ſell his ſhoes, but hee muſt needs ſell or ſhew his laſts,<note place="margin">Scultet. meth. concionandi, Artis eſt ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lare artem.</note> whereby hee maketh them? It is art to conceale art. 3. There is none ſo learned, but he may learne ſomething from the very meaneſt, even from thoſe that bee farre his inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours in gifts, as <hi>Apollos</hi> did of <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 18.26.</note> a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Teacher, and well read in the Word, of a ſilly Tent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker, and weake woman. 4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> As they are not alwayes the richeſt merchants, which out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly make the greateſt ſhow, ſo are not they the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Clerkes which make moſt ſhew of their cunning. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 5. Thou commeſt to Church to learne, not to teach. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 6. Though lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning be required in a Miniſter, yet is it plaine preaching that gaines mens ſoules unto God. 7. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 
                     <hi>None forbids to ſpeake with tongues, if it bee to edification.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.39 1 Cor. 14.18.19.</note> 8. S. <hi>Paul</hi> a learned ſcholler thus ſaith, <hi>I thanke my God, J
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:184293:61"/>ſpeake with tongues more then you all, yet in the Church I had rather ſpeake five words with my underſtanding, that by my voyce I might teach others alſo, then ten thouſand words in an unknowne tongue.</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> 9. Haſt thou not heard many a learned Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon?<note place="margin">Jſa. 28.11.</note> that being fulfilled which in the law is written, <hi>with men of other tongues,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.21.</note> 
                     <hi>and with other lips will J ſpeake unto this people,</hi> yet for all that wouldeſt thou not heare. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> 10. A Miniſter is to gaine mens ſoules unto God,<note place="margin">Act. 12.21, &amp;c.</note> not ſeeke applauſe unto himſelfe with <hi>Herod.</hi> 11. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> How many are there which hearing learned Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, will thereupon cenſure the Preachers, as if thereby they did affect applauſe, ſought themſelves, were ambitious, vaine glorious. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> 12. <hi>What hath</hi> Horace <hi>to doe with the Pſalter,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Hier. ad Euſt. de cuſtod. Vir.</note> Virgil <hi>with the Goſpel, or</hi> Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>with the Epiſtles?</hi> as S. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom</hi> ſaith.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:184293:61"/> II. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> 
                     <hi>His life is not anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his doctrine.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A.</note> A. 1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Though there can be no more noyſome ſmell, then the ſmell of a can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, yet will men rather endure it, then live in darkneſſe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. The Scribes and Phariſees lived ſcandalouſly, in ſo much that our Saviour did often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend them, yet was this his direction;<note place="margin">Mat. 23.2, 3.</note> 
                     <hi>The Scribes and the Phariſees ſit in</hi> Moſes <hi>ſeat, all therefore whatſoever they bid you obſerve, that obſerve and doe, but doe not yee after their workes, for they ſay, and doe not.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">III. <hi>He hath done me wrong.</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> A. How? wherein?<note place="margin">A.</note> By ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king againſt thee in the Pulpit; Who is able to juſtifie the ſame? Thou art, but thou art a party, and through ſelfe-love maiſt be miſtaken. Others are, but are not they pick-thankes and flatterers? yea, are not both of you guiltie of the ſame ſinne? But commeſt thou unto
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:184293:62"/>the Phyſician, and wilt thou not let him rip up thy wounds? Complaineſt thou of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe of ſinne, and wilt thou take no purge to remove it? Thou complaineſt that the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter hath wronged thee in thy name and reputation, and wilt thou wrong thine owne ſoule?</p>
                  <p n="4">IIII. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IIII"/> 
                     <hi>He continueth long in his Sermons,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A.</note> 
                     <hi>and wearieth his hearers.</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> A. 1. It is peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture not ordinary with him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It is recorded of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> upon occaſion offered, hee did at one time <hi>continue his ſpeech untill midnight,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 20.7. &amp; 28.23.</note> and at another, <hi>from morning till evening.</hi> 3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thou canſt without being wearied ſtay twice as long a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thy vaine paſtimes, then tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> doeſt at Church. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. Though every Preacher is an much as in him lyeth to prevent wearineſſe and irkeſomeneſſe in his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,<note place="margin">Lorin. in Acta. p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>g. <hi>591.</hi>
                     </note> and ſo (ordinarily) no to exceed his houre, yet are no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="109" facs="tcp:184293:62"/>hearers ſo to tie Gods Word,<note place="margin">Sed &amp; Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor meminerit, non eſſe alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gandum ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum Dei. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> or ſtint his Spirit, as if it were not lawfull at ſome times upon ſpeciall occaſions to exceed that time.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. 4.</hi> The matter delivered.<note place="margin">The matter delivered.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">I. <hi>Jt is not worth the hearing.</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> A. 1.<note place="margin">A.</note> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> That muſt needs bee a poore Sermon whereby thou maiſt not reape ſome profit. 2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſinne is the Preachers not thine. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. By thy watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thou ſhalt bee able to diſcerne the ſpirits, whether they are of God, or not, and thereupon encourage, admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, pitty, or pray for them. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. Is there no Sermon delivered by any Miniſter that relliſhed thy palate? Is there none of them worth the hearing? when there are (as when are there not?) thou ſhouldeſt not then ſleepe by thine owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. 5. But being aſleepe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> how canſt thou tell that thy Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:184293:63"/>delivers nothing worth the hearing? ſurely thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiteſt it, or faineſt it (as the ſouldiers which watched the Sepulchre gave out,<note place="margin">Mat. 28.13.</note> that <hi>the Diſciples came by night, and ſtole Chriſt away while they ſlept</hi>) for know that thou canſt not.<note place="margin">Ob.</note> But thou wilt ſay, thou haſt often heard him ſo preach, let it bee granted, what then? doth it therefore follow that he doth alwayes preach?<note place="margin">Reſp. Eraſ. apophth. lib <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> yea, I make no queſtion, but (as <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> being aſleepe whilſt <hi>Machetes</hi> his cauſe was pleaded before him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore having againſt equity de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined againſt him upon his appeale to him being awake, and better notice taken there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, repealed his ſentence,) ſo whereas thou condemneſt thy Preacher being aſleepe, thou wouldſt juſtifie him being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake. 6. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
                     <note place="margin">1 King. 22.8.</note> But as <hi>Ahab</hi> hated <hi>Micaiah</hi> (for that <hi>hee did not prophecie good concerning him
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:184293:63"/>but evill</hi>) doeſt thou not hate thy Miniſter? beareſt thou him no grudge? If it bee for well-doing, neither ſhalt thou eſcape puniſhment, nor hee loſe his reward. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 7. Others bleſſe God for it, acknowledge themſelves to be edified by it, and in their daily practiſe conforme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unto it, and why ſhould not thy ſaying and doing be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable unto theirs?</p>
                  <p n="2">II. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> 
                     <hi>It is the very ſame before inſiſted on.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A.</note> 1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Did not S. <hi>Paul</hi> the like (and that at the earneſt entreaty even of thoſe which heard him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.) So <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe,<note place="margin">Act. 13.42.</note> Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> and before them the <hi>Prophets?</hi> 2. Is there no alteration? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Though haply the ſubject bee the ſame, yet is the proſecution thereof diſtinct and different, as being at one time handled <hi>catechetically</hi> by way of <hi>que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion</hi> and <hi>anſwer,</hi> at another, by way of <hi>common place,</hi> at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:184293:64"/>by way of <hi>doctrine,</hi> and <hi>Vſe,</hi> at another by-way of <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphraſe,</hi> and the like. 3. Haſt thou indeed amended by that which thou haſt formerly heard? Thou haſt not. Thou ſhouldſt then bee content, yea, willing and deſirous to heare the ſame things againe and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, untill they ſhall worke on thee, that for which they were at the firſt intended and delivered. Being addicted to whoredome, thou ſhouldſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially affect ſuch Sermons (though often repeated, and long inſiſted upon) which may withdraw thee there-from. The like may be ſaid of every other ſinne. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. When <hi>Iehojakim</hi> had burnt the roll which <hi>Jeremiah</hi> had written,<note place="margin">Ier. 36.32.</note> the Lord comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his Prophet, to write it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new, whereunto were added <hi>many of the like words.</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 5. If the very ſame formerly delivered tooke the Preacher more then two houres (it ſelfe but an
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:184293:64"/>houre long) in penning it, it will take thee farre more to conceive or remember it.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. <hi>It is invective,</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> 
                     <hi>moſt times in the generall, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in particular.</hi> In gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. <hi>A man cannot bee a little joviall with his friends, or ſweare an oath, but it is brought up in the pulpit, and takes up a good part of the Sermon.</hi> In particular; <hi>There is ſcarce a Sermon preached, wherein the Preacher to my great diſcredit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ymeth not at me.</hi> A.<note place="margin">A.</note> To the Generall,<note place="margin">To the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall.</note> 1. Whatſoever is ſinne is to bee ſpoken againſt, how ſmall ſoever the ſame ſeemeth unto many, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> if any at all. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. When thou ſhalt indeed make conſcience of thy wayes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hou wilt abſtaine as from ſinne, ſo from the very appearance thereof. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. The Word is of ſuch a piercing nature, that it <hi>divides betweene the narrow and the bones,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 4.12.</note> and taketh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice aſwell of the ſmalleſt as
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:184293:65"/>of the greateſt ſinnes. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                     <note place="margin">Gat. ſpirit. watch. pag. <hi>46</hi>
                     </note> 4. <hi>Can wee not uſe Gods creatures</hi> (as one ſaith) <hi>unleſſe wee abuſe them, and make that the bain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> and poyſon of our ſoules, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> was given us to be the food an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſtay of our bodyes?</hi> or <hi>can we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> not bee merry, unleſſe wee mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the divell our play-fellow? I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> there no mirth at all but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſwearing and ſwaggering, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in blaſpheming of Gods bleſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> name? Is our mirth nothing worth if it be not mixed wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> prophanoſſe?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">To the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</note> farre be it fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> us to bee thus merry. To th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> particular. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. How knowe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thou that hee aymes at thee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> hath he confeſſed ſo much, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> rather doth not thy guilty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, take occaſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon to accuſe thee? If <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> thou ſhouldſt bleſſe God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> his Word, that hath wrough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſo effectually on thee. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thou the onely bad man in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pariſh? the onely drunka<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſwearer, adulterer, coveto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="115" facs="tcp:184293:65"/>perſon, &amp;c. are there not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as bad as thy ſelfe? There are. Why then may not the Preacher be conceived to ſpeake againſt them, not againſt thee? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. It is not thy perſon, but thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>innes which are aymed at, whereof when thou ſhalt once <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e rid, of them thou ſhalt heare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o more. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. The leſſe thou art <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oothed in thy ſinnes, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er paines are taken to reclaime <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hee there-from; the more the Preacher ſtrives to make thee aſhamed thereof, the greater is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>is love unto thee; ſo ſhalt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ou find it in time, though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ow thou doeſt not, thou wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eſt not.</p>
                  <p n="4">IIII. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IIII"/> 
                     <hi>It is frequently of hell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd damnation, and ſo enough <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o drive a man into deſperation.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A.</note> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 1. <hi>The law is a ſchoole-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>er to bring us to Chriſt,</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>er can any bee raiſed up by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>angelicall conſolations,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.26.</note> who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> not firſt throwne downe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> legall comminations. Firſt
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:184293:66"/>muſt Preachers bee <hi>Boanerges,</hi> ſonnes of thunder, then <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaſſes,</hi> ſonnes of conſolation. 2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> We are to preach as well of judgement, as of mercy: dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, as ſalvation; hell, as heaven: the torments of the one, as joyes of the other. So preached the <hi>Prophets.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſa. 30.27. &amp;c. Luk. 11.42. &amp;c. 2 Theſ. 1.8. Rev. 15.6, 7.</note> So <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> This ſeemeth figured in that viſion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>John; The ſeven Angels which came out of the Temple, though clothed in pure and white lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen, and having their breaſt girded with golden girdles, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> had the ſeven plagues, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> them one of the foure beaſt gave ſeven golden vialls f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> of the wrath of God, to pour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> them out upon the earth.</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Wounds thee, that it may hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> thee; caſts thee downe, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> may raiſe thee up; drives th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> as it were into deſperation, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> thou maiſt truly repent, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> taine unto humiliation.</p>
                  <p n="5">V. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> 
                     <hi>Jt is often errone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="117" facs="tcp:184293:66"/>and hereticall, wherwith</hi> (were I awake) <hi>I could not but bee in danger to bee infected, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe forced to preſent the broacher thereof to his utter undoing.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A.</note> A. 1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Not every thing which thou conceiveſt to bee erroneous and hereticall, is therefore to bee ſo reputed. Thereof Gods word muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine. 2. Thou knoweſt not, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> but as the broacheer thereof, was by Satan ſtirred up to broach thoſe errours; ſo Gods Spirit will draw him to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantation. 3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> A Preacher may through ignorance or heedleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe miſtake, and afterwards upon good ground revoke the ſame. 4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> If thou ſhouldſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve any to continue in their errour, thou couldſt doe the Church no better ſervice, then through thy detecting of them, to have them cut off, whereat others haply through feare or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>avour will connive.</p>
                  <p n="6">VI. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> 
                     <hi>Jt is that wherewith I
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:184293:67"/>am already very well acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> A.<note place="margin">A.</note> 1. Art thou the onely hearer? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Though thou knoweſt the truth, yet peradventure o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the aſſembly doe not who are therefore to bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in thoſe very things, which thou knoweſt, that they alſo may know the ſame. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> thou knoweſt ſo much, why then is not thy practiſe anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. 3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Werſt thou not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> partiall judge, thou mighte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> truly and ingenuouſly confeſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that through the Word (though out of the mouth of a weak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> man by thee too much deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) thy knowledge is dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bettered and augmented 4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Though thou knoweſt much yet by the Word thou mai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> learne to know more, which the Word knoweth of thee namely, <hi>that thou knoweſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing yet as thou oughtest t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> know.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">VII. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VII"/> 
                     <hi>It is ſuch, as where<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> I have not profited all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="119" facs="tcp:184293:67"/>while, though I have beene an hearer thereof theſe many yeares; yea, and have beene ſo watchfull, as that J have not given leave unto mine eyes to ſleepe, nor my eye-lids to ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thereat. I am no leſſe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, then before; no leſſe cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ous, malicious, laſcivious, and the like.</hi> A.<note place="margin">A.</note> The woman with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he bloody iſſue was diſeaſed <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>welve yeeres,</hi> yet at the length <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ured.<note place="margin">Mat. 9.20.</note> The woman which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ad the ſpirit of infirmity for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he ſpace of 18. <hi>yeares,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 13.16.</note> and was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>owed together, and could in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o wiſe lift up her ſelfe, yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as at the length looſed from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>er bonds.<note place="margin">Joh. 5.9.</note> The man of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alſie was diſeaſed for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pace of 38. <hi>yeares,</hi> and yet at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ength at Chriſts command, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y his power, roſe, tooke up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is bed and walked. <hi>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ind bloweth where it liſteth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd thou heareſt the ſound <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hereof, but canſt not tell,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joh. 3.8.</note> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hence it commeth, and whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:184293:68"/>it goeth; So is every one that is borne of the Spirit.</hi> Abide an hearer, waite Gods good leiſure, for aſſuredly if thou belongeſt to God, thou ſhalt heare ſomething at the length which will doe thee good.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. 5.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The perſons reproving it.</note> The Perſons repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> 
                     <hi>They have little to doe that meddle herewith.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A.</note> A. They are never out of their calling which would worke in thee a diſlike of ſinne, and further thy ſalvation, whether in this o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> other particulars. Some are enabled to encounter the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. Every one may ſeeme ſufficiently qualified to cop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with this.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> 
                     <hi>Such often-times as are moſt faultie herein doe moſt fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> fault hereat.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A.</note> A. Though their zeale againſt this ſinne in thee doth not excuſe or tolerate
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:184293:68"/>them thus to ſinne, yet art not thou thus to ſinne, becauſe thy reprovers may be juſtly repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for the ſame.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Remedies for the cure of this ſleeping evill.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is obſerved that thoſe grounds doe beare moſt corne, and are freeſt from weeds, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are ſowne, are duly prepared, and after the ſeed is ſowne, are carefully harrowed,<note place="margin">What is to be done to avoid Church-ſleeping.</note> well fenced in, and diligently looked unto; So thoſe which would profit by the Word, and be free from this drowſie di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, muſt both <hi>before they come to Church,</hi> when <hi>they are come to Church,</hi> and when <hi>they are returned home</hi> ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves on worke.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:184293:69"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. 1.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Before we come to Church.</note> Before wee come to Curch we must,</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                     <hi>Take notice of Gods great goodneſſe towards us, in affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his Word unto us;</hi> the ſame being ſo needfull, as With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which our condition could not bee but indeed miſerable, the ſame being ſo profitable,<note place="margin">Amos 8.11. Rev. 2.5.</note> as that no greater judgement can befall a land, then the remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall thereof therefrom, no greater happineſſe then its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                     <hi>Examine our owne hearts throughly, for what cauſe, and to what end it is, that wee goe to Church;</hi> as whether it be not more, for feare, then love; out of cuſtome, then conſcience; to ſee and to bee ſeene, then in obedience unto Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement. This is <hi>to ponder the path of our feet;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 4.26. Prov. 14.15.</note> and ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>the prudent man looketh well to his going.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="123" facs="tcp:184293:69"/> 3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                     <hi>Obſerve our naturall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and by what meanes it commeth to paſſe, that ſleepe at Church ſeazeth upon us,</hi> as whether it comes not, through long waking; exceſſive eating and drinking,<note place="margin">Gen. 22.5.</note> diſtracting cares of the world (for as <hi>Abraham</hi> when hee went to ſacrifice his ſonne upon the Mount, left his aſſe and ſervants at the foot of the hill; So when we come to the holy hill of God, with the Congregation, wee muſt aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don all by buſineſſes) preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice againſt the perſon of the Teacher. Pride for ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of knowledge received,<note place="margin">Amputemus cauſas morbi, ut morbus pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riter aufera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Hier.</note> carnall ſecuritie or the like; for the cauſe being knowne and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, the effect will of it ſelfe ceaſe. Upon this diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very will enſue an holy jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, whereby we ſhall be made ſo wary, as that wee ſhall not truſt our ſelves, but uſe meanes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o prevent this evill; for as they that know themſelves to
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:184293:70"/>have a weake ſtomacke are very chary of their diet, ſo hee that is ſuſpicious of himſelfe, and jealous of his owne drowſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and proneneſſe thereto will bee carefull to avoid the ſame. And as they that have gun-powder in their houſes, are carefull that fire come not neere it, ſo finding our corruption as gun-powder, and the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned cauſes of drowſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as fire, wee ſhall ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour that they may not meet together; yea, hereupon (if wee ſhall at any time be ſtirred up to a diſlike of the Teacher, to an admiration of our owne knowledge, and the like) wee ſhall thus argue. If I ſhall give way unto this ſuggeſtion, then will ſleepe ſeaze on mee, then ſhall I loſe the benefit of the Word, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 12.9.</note> 
                     <hi>Labour for a true hatred and detestation of this ſinne</hi> Never ſhall wee cloſely cleav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> unto that which is good, till w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="125" facs="tcp:184293:70"/>have brought our hearts to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and abhorre that which is evill, were this throughly wrought, there needed no rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toricke to diſſwade us from Church-ſleeping.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 13.16</note> As <hi>Amnon</hi> loathing <hi>Thamar</hi> thruſt her out of doores,<note place="margin">Pro. 8.13.</note> ſo <hi>(it being the feare of God to hate evill)</hi> would we drive it away. And as a man cannot indure the ſent or ſavour of the meate which he loatheth, our very hearts would riſe againſt the ſame.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>Hunger after the Word.</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Bodily hunger may occaſion ſleepe, or ſleepe may ſeaze e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven on the hungry (according to the Proverb,<note place="margin">Vulpieſurienti ſomnus obre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit. Eraſ. chil.</note> 
                     <hi>Sleepe commeth upon the hungry fox</hi>) but this hunger driveth away ſleepe, for as the ſtomacke hungering for meat, cannot bee contented without it, ſo neither can our ſoules without the Word, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once taken with an earneſt deſire thereof.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 23.15</note> Great was <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> longing for a little water
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:184293:71"/>of the Well of <hi>Bethleem; Oh!</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that one would give mee drinke of the water of the Well of Bethleem, which is by the gate</hi>) but much more ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement was it for the Word.<note place="margin">Pſal. 42.2.</note> 
                     <hi>My ſoule</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thirſteth for God, for the living God, when ſhall I come and appeare before God?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 84.2.</note> And againe, <hi>My ſoule longeth, yea even faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for the courts of the Lord.</hi> (Aſſuredly had <hi>David</hi> had leave at this time to have come to the hearing of the Word, he would not have ſlept thereat.) And who will not hunger after the Word, if hee doe but 1.<note place="margin">By what meanes an hunger after the Word may be wrought in us.</note> Take a taſt thereof in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate by reading and meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Hereby the ſoule cannot but get much both inſtruction and conſolation. 2. Conſider the excellencie, neceſſity, and utilitie of the ſame, whereof I have already ſpoken at large:<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.10. Prov. 3.15. and 8.10.</note> and wereof both <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Salomon</hi> did make ſo much ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:184293:71"/>that they eſteemed it above gold, ſilver, rubies, and what not?</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
                     <hi>Reſolve to attend unto, and make conſcience of the ſacred ordinance of preashing there delivered.</hi> as <hi>Job,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Job 31.1.</note> 
                     <hi>J have made a covenant with my eyes, why then ſhould I thinke upon a maide?</hi> So doe we make a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, as with our eares to heare, ſo with our eyes not to ſleepe at Church. Such was <hi>Davids</hi> religious care for the Arke,<note place="margin">Pſal. 132.4</note> that <hi>hee would not give ſleepe to his eyes, nor ſlumber to his eye-lids, untill he found out a place for the Lord, and habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation for the mighty God of Jacob;</hi> And ſuch muſt ours bee at the Word, if wee would have any communion with God in that ſacred ordinance. <hi>Jacob</hi> being <hi>Labans</hi> ſhepheard,<note place="margin">Gen. 31.40.</note> and making conſcience of his duty, <hi>his ſleepe</hi> (by night) <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from his eyes,</hi> and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly ſo would ſleepe depart
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:184293:72"/>from ours, (eſpecially by day) if we made conſcience of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Word.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 
                     <hi>Vſe the creatures ſparing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> both ſleepe (for what is ſaid of drinking water, may be ſaid of this,<note place="margin">Quo plùs ſunt potae, plùs ſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untur aquae.</note> 
                     <hi>the more it is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, the more it is deſired</hi>) and meate and drinke; for when men have over-liberally eate and drunke, they are wont to bee heavie and drowſie, ready to ſlumber as they ſit, fit for nothing, but for ſleepe. Such exceſſe, as it is a meanes even to drowne the mind, and by caſting reaſon and underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding into a deepe and deadly ſleepe, to make men unable to watch againſt the motions of ſinne, to ſhut the doore of the heart againſt all vertues, and to ſet it open to all vices, ſo much more ſtupifieth it the body. contrarily,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.6.</note> 
                     <hi>Sobrietie</hi> is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeciall helpe to <hi>vigilancie,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 47.</note> which therefore the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> are uſually wont to <hi>joyne</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <pb n="129" facs="tcp:184293:72"/> 8. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 
                     <hi>Conſider whither wee are going, before whom to what end, and who wee are?</hi> To Gods houſe, into the preſence of the God of heaven, to bee made partakers of the Word for the good of our ſoules, wee being (as of our ſelves) of all others the moſt unworthy.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> 
                     <hi>Pray,</hi> as for the <hi>Preacher</hi> (that <hi>his lips may preſerve knowlede;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mal. 2.7:</note> he may be <hi>faithfull</hi> in delivering the whole <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell</hi> of God unto us,<note place="margin">Act. 20.27.</note> and hee may powerfully and wiſely ſpeake to our conſciences.<note place="margin">Rom. 1.16.</note>) and the <hi>Word</hi> read or preached (that it may bee unto us the <hi>power of God unto our ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>2.16.</note> the <hi>ſavour of life unto life,</hi> and as <hi>good ſeed</hi> ſowne in a <hi>good ground</hi>) ſo for our <hi>ſelves</hi> and <hi>others,</hi> that our eares may be <hi>attentive,</hi> our eyes <hi>fixed</hi> on the <hi>Preacher,</hi> our <hi>mindes</hi> bee <hi>opened</hi> to underſtand, and our <hi>hearts</hi> and affections <hi>ſanctified</hi> to <hi>obey</hi> the holy <hi>Word.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:184293:73"/>
                  <p>Ob. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>I cannot poſſibly ſpare ſo much time from my Calling, as to thinke on theſe things; or be thus prepared.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                     </label> 1. As our Saviour unto <hi>Martha;</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                     <hi>Martha, Martha, thou art carefull,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 10, 41:4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>and troubled about many things, but one thing is needfull; and Mary hath choſen that good part which ſhall not bee taken away from her,</hi> ſo may I unto thee. The ſoule is to bee preferred unto the body, and thou art more carefull of this, then that.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                     <hi>Bodily exerciſe profiteth little, but godlineſſe is profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table unto all things, having promiſe of the life that now is, and of that which is to come.</hi> 3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                     <hi>Seeke ye firſt the kingdome of God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.8.</note> 
                     <hi>and his righteouſneſſe, and all theſe things ſhall bee added unto you.</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. Even in the doing of the workes of our Calling, wee may both medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, pray, reſolve, &amp;c. and ſo that bee no let to this. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Wee
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:184293:73"/>omit not our bodily recreation notwithſtanding the workes of our calling, and why ſhould wethis? 6. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Wee take time to finne, and why ſhould wee not take time to prevent ſinne?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. 2.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">When wee come to Church.</note> When wee come to Church wee muſt</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Generall;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">In generall.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                     <hi>Take heed unto our affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> (which the <hi>Preacher</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth by theſe words) <hi>Keepe thy foot when thou goeſt to the houſe of God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.1.</note> 
                     <hi>and be more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to heare, then to give the ſacrifice of fooles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                     <hi>Get our eyes to bee anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with eye-ſalve, that we may ſee,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 3.18.</note> and <hi>our eares open that wee may heare.</hi> Remembring that as God hath beſtowed upon us eyes and eares, ſo when wee are come into his houſe, both muſt be ſet on worke. As our <hi>eyes</hi> muſt bee <hi>ſeeing,</hi> ſo muſt our <hi>eares</hi> bee <hi>hearing,</hi> and <hi>obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient,</hi>
                     <pb n="132" facs="tcp:184293:74"/>as we our ſelves <hi>ſwift to beare.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iam. 1.19.</note> to this purpoſe is that ſo often reiterated phraſe, <hi>Hee that hath eares to heare,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 11.15:</note> 
                     <hi>let him heare.</hi> Yea, as it is uſuall for one that is drowſie to waſh and rub his eyes, or that feeleth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny impediments in his eares to picke them; ſo when wee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive drowſineſſe to creepe on us at <hi>Church,</hi> wee muſt then rouſe up our ſelves.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                     <hi>Bee poſſeſſed with Gods feare,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſa. 66.2. 1 Sam. 4.13.</note> that <hi>wee may tremble at the Word.</hi> As <hi>Eli</hi> whilſt hee ſate on a ſtooleby the way ſide, watched, <hi>becauſe his heart trembled for the Arke of God;</hi> So if when wee are at Church, our hearts ſhall tremble in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of our preſent danger through Satan, wee ſhall be kept waking.<note place="margin">Dan. 2.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> being troubled, <hi>his ſleepe went from him,</hi> ſo were wee troubled for ſinne, or did ſtand in awe of god, becauſe of the ſame, it would not fall on us.
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:184293:74"/>Griefe and ſorrow occaſion ſleepe,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk. 22.44.</hi> Vigilabis, ſi ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mebis. Auguſt. Timor domini janitor animi. Ber. formido facit ſolicitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem. Ter. <hi>Pſal. 4.4. Pro. 16.6.</hi>
                     </note> but feare and care make vigilant and watchfull. This is as a Porter ſet at the doore of our ſoule; and will alſo keepe our eyes waking. There is no affection more watchfull then this. <hi>Stand in awe and ſinne not;</hi> yea, as by this men <hi>depart from evill,</hi> ſo ſhall wee through it, from this of ſleeping at Church. This being kept freſh in our hearts, will make us carefull to ſhunne, and fearefull to doe ought that may offend him whom we feare. In feare of invaſion men are wont to keepe due watch and ward, but when there is no ſuch dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger miſdoubted, like the men of <hi>Lachiſh,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iudg. 18.7.</note> they are the more careleſſe and ſecure, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon are often upon the ſudden oppreſſed. At the hearing of the Word, wee are at all times in danger of the aſſaults of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, there is then neither time nor place to ſleepe thereat.
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:184293:75"/>The <hi>Crane</hi> which is by the reſt appointed for <hi>Sentinell,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Franc. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſ. de Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cub. &amp; vigil.</note> hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in its foot a ſmall ſtone, whereby it may be kept awake; and <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, held in the night a ſilver ball, over a brazen baſon, that if he ſhould fleepe, by the ſound thereof he might be awaked, ſuch a ſtone, ſuch a ball, will Gods feare prove unto us, to keepe us from Church-ſleeping.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                     <hi>Bee perſwaded that the Scriptures to bee read, or the Sermon ready to be uttered, may doe us more good, then all thoſe we have yet heard.</hi> Yea, that they may be the laſt which we ſhall ever heare, as that very houre,<note place="margin">Platar.</note> the laſt of our lives. As <hi>Miltiades</hi> his triumph hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> from ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping; So did we conſider the benefit of the Word, and duly weigh what good God may thereby convey into our ſoules, (as he hath done to others) we would queſtionleſſe not ſleepe
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:184293:75"/>thereat.<note place="margin">Ecclus 31.1.</note> 
                     <hi>The care of riches driveth away ſleepe,</hi> ſaith the ſonne of <hi>Sirach.</hi> So did wee care for the durable riches which the Word affordeth, we would not ſleepe thereat.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
                     <hi>Conſider,</hi> that as <hi>God</hi> ſleepeth not for our <hi>good,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 121.4.</note> and the <hi>divell</hi> ſleepeth not for our <hi>hurt;</hi> So if we ſhould ſleepe at Church, God would leave us, and the divell would make a prey of us.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
                     <hi>Call to mind,</hi> that there will be ſtore of <hi>witneſſes</hi> to <hi>riſe</hi> up againſt us on the <hi>day of judgement,</hi> if wee ſhall thus ſin. Then will the <hi>Lord</hi> ſay, I ſpake unto them, but they would not heare me; I was preſent with mine owne ordinance, but they would not looke upon mee. Then will <hi>Chriſt ſay;</hi> I offered, my ſelfe unto them, but they would none of me; I called up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, but they would not anſwer me; I would have ſhewed them what I had done
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:184293:76"/>for them, but they did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard me. Then will the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> ſay, I would have ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into their hearts, I would have there lodged; I would have made the Word to take roote in them, but by their ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping thereat they grieved me. Then will <hi>the Word</hi> ſay; They deſpiſed me. The <hi>Saints</hi> ſay, They offended us. The <hi>ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> ſay, They hardened us in our ſinnes, and occaſioned our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Word.</p>
                  <p>It were not amiſſe,<note place="margin">Dan. 5.5, 6.</note> that (as <hi>Belſhazar</hi> was driven from his carnall mirth by viewing the hand-writing which appeared on the wall) they that are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to ſleepe at Church, would imagine at leaſt, that it were written over their Pewes, <hi>Awake thou that ſleepeſt.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eph. 5 14.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>In particular, in hearing we muſt uſe,<note place="margin">In particular uſe.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                     <hi>Attention,</hi> which is when the whole body,<note place="margin">Attention.</note> eſpecially the eare and the eye, are reverently
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:184293:76"/>compoſed about hearing the Word. The eare;<note place="margin">Act. 10.33.</note> as <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his houſhold were alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, waiting for <hi>Peter</hi> to heare the Word. The eye;<note place="margin">Luk. 4 28.</note> as <hi>the eyes of all that were in the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue were faſtened on him;</hi> that is, on Chriſt when hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to teach them; wee muſt with <hi>Mary</hi> ſit at <hi>Jeſus</hi> feet,<note place="margin">Luk. 10.39.</note> and heare his Word. Doth not the hungry ſtomack watch for meat? and ſhould not wee watch for the food of our ſoules?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Intention,</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> which is of the mind,<note place="margin">Intention.</note> when wee diligently marke thoſe things which wee are taught; We ſee by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that in a deepe meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though our eyes be fixed on ſome certaine object, yet wee ſmally regard it, ſo if the mind bee not preſent aſwell as the body, all is to no purpoſe. To this purpoſe is that of <hi>Salomon,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 2.2:</note> 
                     <hi>Cauſe thine eare to hearken, and encline thine heart to wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:184293:77"/>and underſtanding.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                     <hi>Retention,</hi> which is of the memorie,<note place="margin">Retention. Luk. 2.52.</note> when wee lay up the word of God in the heart, as the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> the ſayings concerning Chriſt. Hee that maketh conſcience here of will hardly ſleepe hereat.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                     <hi>Devotion,</hi> which calleth for an heart truly religious.<note place="margin">Devotion.</note> A devout ſoule, never heares of mercy but with comfort; of Gods juſtice but with feare; of his truth without aſſenting to it, of his workes without ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, and where devotion dwelleth, drowſineſſe is ſhut out.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
                     <hi>Subjection.</hi> God ſpeakes, and muſt not wee heare?<note place="margin">Subjection.</note> yea, yeeld obedience therunto, how repugnant ſoever the ſame ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth unto our corrupt nature? now how can there bee obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, when there is no ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction? how ſubjection, where knowledge wanteth? how knowledge bee had without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction?
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:184293:77" rendition="simple:additions"/>how receive inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction without hearing it? how heare it if ſleepe bee enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained?</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>Diſcretion.</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> The eare is to the ſoule,<note place="margin">Diſcretion.</note> as the mouth is to the body; The mouth refuſeth unſavoury meat, that may bee hurtfull to the body, ſo muſt our eares reject erroneous and hereticall doctrine. But if the mouth bee out of taſte, what food will it not receive, how noyſome ſoever? ſo if the eares bee dull and heavy, will not falſhood be embraced for truth? mens traditions, as Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements?</p>
                  <p>Thoſe that we may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter performe,<note place="margin">Means wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme thoſe.</note> we muſt</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Remember that we are in Gods preſence;</hi> at <hi>Bethel,</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Gods houſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.8: 1 Cor. 11.10</note> and that hee both ſeeth us, and ſpeaketh to us, we muſt <hi>ſet the Lord alwayes before our eyes,</hi> eſpecially at this time. If <hi>Paul</hi> will have women <hi>reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently to behave themſelves
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:184293:78" rendition="simple:additions"/>in the congregation, becauſe of the Angels;</hi> much more ought all both men and women, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have themſelves reverently, becauſe of the preſence of God, who is the Lord both of men and Angels. This was that which kept <hi>David</hi> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe;<note place="margin">Pſa. 119.168</note> 
                     <hi>I have kept</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>thy Precepts and Teſtimonies, for all my wayes are in thy ſight.</hi> Doe wee at any time begin to find our ſelves drowſie at Church? ſpeake we thus unto our owne ſoules, Should I thus doe in Gods preſence? yea, as the Lord called <hi>Samuel;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Sam: 3.10.</note> 
                     <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel, Samuel,</hi> and the ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter unto <hi>Jonah,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ionah 1.6.</note> 
                     <hi>What mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt thou, O ſleeper?</hi> So doe we imagine that the Lord ſpeaketh unto every one of us in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; <hi>Why ſleepeſt thou, O ſluggard? awake thou that ſleepeſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                     <hi>Stand up.</hi> It is very me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable, which is reported of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great by <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Euſeb. de vita Conſtant. lib. <hi>4</hi> cap. <hi>33.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <pb n="141" facs="tcp:184293:78" rendition="simple:additions"/>Being requeſted by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines that diſputed before him, that after long ſtanding hee would ſit downe and take his eaſe, anſwered; <hi>It is an impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thing to heare negligently diſputations concerning God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                     <hi>Rouſe up our ſelves ever and anone;</hi> as the cocke clap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth his wings, that he may the more cheerfully crow, wee muſt <hi>ſtirre up the grace of God in us;</hi> yea,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.6.</note> wee muſt check our ſelves when wee perceive our drowſineſſe.<note place="margin">Prov. 6.9.</note> 
                     <hi>How long wilt thou ſleepe, O ſluggard? when wilt thou ariſe out of thy ſleepe?</hi> We muſt ſay unto our ſelves, <hi>art thou in a way to heaven? will the Lord bee pleaſed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                     <hi>Vſe now and then ſhort and ſudden ejaculations,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 13.5.</note> as in the words of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>lighten mine eyes leſt I ſleepe the ſleepe of death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> 
                     <hi>Goe along with the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher from point to point,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:184293:79"/>the Word in particular to the part affected, as the ſtomacke conveieth nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to each member. Heare we comfort? wee are to apply it to our feare, as Gods promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes againſt diſtruſt; So if wee heare threatnings againſt ſinne, whether whoredome, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, pride, or any elſe, and know our ſelves guilty thereof, wee are to apply it to our ſelves for our humiliation, ſaying of both upon occaſion; This is for mee; This promiſe; This comfort; This threatning.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. 3.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">After we are come from Church, uſe</note> After we are come from Church we muſt</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                     <hi>Call our ſelves to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count how wee behaved our ſelves at Church,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> as about Church-ſleeping, whether wee be guilty thereof, or not, that upon our not guilty wee may expreſſe our thankfulneſſe,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>See</hi> Gatak. Spirit. Watch pag. <hi>81.</hi>
                     </note> as upon guilty remorſe and humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="143" facs="tcp:184293:79"/> 2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                     <hi>Recall and revolve in our minds ſuch gracious inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Meditation.</note> 
                     <hi>as the Word afforded us;</hi> thus bringing into out remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, what we heard former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delivered, as the <hi>Bereans</hi> who as <hi>they received the Word with all readineſſe of mind, ſearched the Scriptures daily, whether thoſe things</hi> (which they heard) <hi>were ſo.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon will ariſe ſuch profit and pleaſure, as that wee ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devour thereafter, not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive our ſelves through unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſleeping, of the good which may bee gained by the Word. This is the very life of hearing, neither can wee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meditation bring the Word into practiſe.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                     <hi>Impart unto others by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition, what the Lord in his Word hath communicated to us,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Repetition.</note> not doing the ſame at ſome one time, but conſtantly (as a duty whereunto we are tied) upon our hearing the Word.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="144" facs="tcp:184293:80"/> 4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                     <hi>Conferre of ſuch things at home,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Conference.</note> 
                     <hi>as have beene delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at Church,</hi> and that eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by way of Catechiſing, or by queſtion and anſwer.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
                     <hi>Put in practiſe ſuch graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous things,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Practiſe.</note> 
                     <hi>as the Word hath revealed unto us.</hi> If thou didſt profit by one Sermon (as aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly thou mighteſt, if thou didſt practiſe, what thou art therin preſcribed) thou wouldſt not ſleepe at the next.<note place="margin">Prompt ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>p. refor. pag <hi>456</hi>
                     </note> A cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Lady having asked her ſervants, whether the Sermon was done, to whom affirming that it was; ſhee anſwered, <hi>It was ſaid, not yet done;</hi> imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that though the Miniſter had performed his part, they had not yet done theirs; that is, though he had taught them, yet they had not yet followed all his inſtructions.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:184293:80"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> The Application of the foregoing diſcourſe for
<list>
                     <item>Reprehenſion.<note place="margin">Vſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion unto Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>Exhortation.</item>
                  </list>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. 1.</hi> Reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of
<list>
                        <item>Preachers.</item>
                        <item>People.</item>
                     </list>
                  </head>
                  <p>Preachers,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                     <hi>Which doe any way occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion this evill,</hi> Whether by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king no paines in their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, by ayming more at ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe unto themſelves, then at Gods glory therein; by delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring erroneous and hereticall doctrine; by wearying their auditors; by leading their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ives ſcandalouſly, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ike.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                     <hi>Which doe not what in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hem lyes to remove this evill.</hi> Should they not at ſometimes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>all into a commendation of
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:184293:81"/>Gods word, to bring their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple into a liking thereof? ſhould they not at other times ſet forth the miſery of ſuch as are without it? ſhould they not now and then inveigh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe, which doe negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently heare it, or ſleepe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at? ſhould they not be as <hi>Boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerges,</hi> even filled with zeale againſt thoſe that thus deſpiſe it? Muſt not their voyces bee lift up as a trumpet, and upon occaſions ſound theſe words of the ſhip-maſter, unto <hi>Jonah, What meaneſt thou,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ionah 1.6.</note> 
                     <hi>O ſleeper?</hi> and that of <hi>Salomon</hi> to the ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard?<note place="margin">Prov. 6.9.</note> 
                     <hi>When wilt thou ariſe out of thy ſleepe? how long wilt thou ſleepe, O ſluggard?</hi> And thoſe of the Spirit,<note place="margin">Eph. 5:14.</note> 
                     <hi>awake thou that ſleepeſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>People,<note place="margin">People:</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                     <hi>Which</hi> (whilſt the Word is taught) <hi>laugh, talke, reade gaze up and downe in every cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and the like,</hi> every of which (through the juſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:184293:81"/>of God,) doth (for the moſt part) end in ſleeping, when the ſenſes are wearied with thoſe, then doe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre unto ſleepe for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Which make a jeſt of it;</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> as if that which doth ſo much diſpleaſe God; ſo much wrong Gods word; ſo much preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice Gods people; ſo much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage Satans kingdome, and hath beene ſo ſeverely puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, were indeed to bee laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at. Unto ſuch I ſay,<note place="margin">Iam. 4.9.</note> 
                     <hi>Bee afflicted, and mourne, and weepe, let your laughter bee turned to mourning, and your joy to heavineſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                     <hi>Which doe what in them lyes to continue in it;</hi> yea, doe ſo love to ſleepe, as that they will further their inclination hereunto, through intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancie, worldly care, ſelfe-conceit, prejudicate opinions, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd the like; thus entertaining <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uch things as may make
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:184293:82"/>them more drowſie.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                     <hi>Which are angry with thoſe that doe awake them;</hi> They come to Church againſt their will; They there ſtay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their will; and if they there heare any thing, it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their will.<note place="margin">Ecclus. 22.7.</note> They love ſleepe, ſet themſelves to ſleepe, and cannot abide to be awaked. Their untoward faces, fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward words <hi>(Let mee alone, what have yee to doe with me? meddle with your ſelves, &amp;c.)</hi> and uncivill behaviour toward thoſe that doe awake them, were worth the obſervation. Wouldſt thou when thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt to Church ſleepe all the while? farre bee it from thee. As the Diſciples unto our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Chriſt being aſleepe,<note place="margin">Mar. 4.38:</note> 
                     <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, careſt thou not that we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> periſh?</hi> So may it be ſaid unto thee that affecteſt drowſineſſe; Careſt thou not though thou periſheſt?<note place="margin">Mar. 4.24.</note> Doſt thou already know too much? or haſt thou
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:184293:82"/>already heard too much? wouldſt thou heare, more ſhould be given unto thee.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
                     <hi>Which being guilty here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Non feneſtra nunc, non fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, non ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus intertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat; (ait Chryſoſtomus) attamen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> audimus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> anguſtia lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>, non aliquid horum. Lorin. in Acta. p. <hi>591.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>doe notwithstanding uſe one or other excuſe for their juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</hi> What canſt thou pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend? long preaching, much crowding, heat, hard labour; and the like? Beware leſt in pleading not guilty unto one ſinne, thou beeſt not guilty of lying, and ſo puniſhed for both.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
                     <hi>Which will not by any meanes bee reclaimed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from.</hi> God calleth thee, as hee did <hi>Samuel,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Sam. 3.3.</note> and wilt thou not heare? Hee would acquaint thee with his will, and ſhall thine eyes bee alwayes heavy? <hi>How long wilt thou ſleep,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 6.9.10.</note> 
                     <hi>O ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard? yet a little ſleep, a little ſlumber, &amp; a little folding of the handsto ſleep.</hi> Knoweſt thou not that many littles make a great, and that but a nappe at a time comes in time, to a good deale
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:184293:83"/>of time? Of old, <hi>they that ſlept,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.7.</note> 
                     <hi>ſlept in the night, as they that were drunke, were drunke in the night;</hi> and wilt thou now ſleepe in the day, and that in Gods houſe? Art thou an Image? or wilt thou make thy ſelfe one? having eyes, ſeeſt thou not?<note place="margin">Mar. 8.18.</note> and having eares, why wilt thou not heare? wouldſt thou die, whilſt thou ſleepeſt at Church? were that the way unto heaven? Not any thing the divell more hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,<note place="margin">Mar. 9.25.</note> then hearing the Word, and ſhouldeſt thou be poſſeſſed with <hi>a deafe divell?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Homer.</note> As it was <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> his chiefeſt care for his owne preſervation to deprive <hi>Polyphemus</hi> of his eye-ſight, ſo is it Satans to deprive thee both of ſeeing and hearing at Church,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.43.</note> for thy deſtruction. As Chriſt came the ſecond and third time, and found his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples aſleepe; So when ſhall one obſerve thee, but aſleepe at Church?<note place="margin">Pro. 29:1:</note> 
                     <hi>Hee that being often
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:184293:83"/>reproved hardeneth his necke, ſhall ſuddenly be deſtroyed, and that without remedie</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon.</hi>) And haſt not thou beene often reproved for this fault, and yet art never the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter?<note place="margin">Deut. 32:1.</note> As both <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets</hi> directed their ſpeech,<note place="margin">Iſa. 1.2.</note> unto the <hi>heavens, earth,</hi> and <hi>mountaines;</hi> ſo might wee well doe, conſidering the generall drowſineſſe, which hath taken hold on moſt men and women. As the Prophet of old,<note place="margin">Iſa. 53.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Who hath beleeved</hi> (ſo may wee now, <hi>who hath heard</hi>) <hi>our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port?</hi> How many like the <hi>dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſe,</hi> ſleepe all Winter, that it may live the better in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; So doe they ſleepe at Church, that they may wake about their worldly buſineſſes.<note place="margin">Eraſ. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pophth.</note> 
                     <hi>Alexander</hi> the <hi>Great</hi> knew himſelfe to bee a man by ſleepe, ſo maiſt thou know thy ſelfe to bee a ſinfull man by ſleeping at Church. What a ſhame is it,<note place="margin">Heb. 5.12.</note> that <hi>when for the time yee ought
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:184293:84"/>to bee Teachers, yee have need that one teach you againe, which bee the firſt Principles of the Oracles of God, and are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſuch as have need of milke, and not of ſtrong meat.</hi> What is the reaſon?<note place="margin">Prompt. ſap. reformat. pag. <hi>456.</hi>
                     </note> how commeth this to paſſe after ſo many Sermons? Even becauſe yee are dull of hearing, either heare not at all, or to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. <hi>Which when the Sermon is done, will not ſticke to cut the points delivered into que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, and diſpute about the ſame, themſelves notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for the moſt part ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving beene aſleepe thereat;</hi> or when they are come from Church will commend the Preacher, and his Sermon, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling how zealous, how lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. how eloquent it was, &amp;c. when as haply they heare but a little thereof. Thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeſt it. It is well (ſo may a ſick perſon commend a phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:184293:84"/>whoſe Phyſick hee never tried) but what profit haſt thou gained thereby? what fruit hath it produced on thee? If none, thou wert no otherwiſe an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, but in imagination.</p>
                  <p>Sect. 2. <hi>Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Preachers.</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Vſe of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation unto Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers.</note>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>People.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Preachers.</p>
                  <p>Be wee carefull as well to prevent this evill, as to remove it, when it ſeazeth on our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors.<note place="margin">Iam. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> As wee are not <hi>to have the faith of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the Lord of glory, with reſpect of perſons.</hi> So let not our Sermons bee with reſpect of perſons, but ſo ſtudy, and ſo preach at all times, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee may enforce hearing eares, and the eyes of all may be ſet on us. Lift wee up our voyces like trumpets, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when we ſhall obſerve our people drowſie; So ſhall wee, nill they, will they, rowſe them up. Endevour wee alſo that our Auditors may truly
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:184293:85"/>love us, as children their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents (for where the man is deſpiſed, how is it poſſible that his doctrine ſhould bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded?) which they will doe, through our love of them, and their ſoules ſalvation. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever may bring our miniſtry into contempt, be wee carefull to avoid, being aſſured that ſuch as ſhall loath our doctrine, (though haply they come to Church, that thereby they may avoid the danger of the law) will rather ſet themſelves to ſleepe, then give eare thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. Such indeed will take ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions at our <hi>doctrine,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing either too harſh, or too mild, too vehement, or too cold, at our <hi>utterance,</hi> as being either too ſlow, or too quicke, at our <hi>voice,</hi> as either being too high, or too low, and at our <hi>converſation,</hi> as being either too looſe, or too auſtere, but wee muſt not be diſcouraged. But why ſhould I offer to inſtruct
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:184293:85"/>you, both knowing what you ſhould doe, and doing what you know?</p>
                  <p>People.<note place="margin">People.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>When thou commeſt unto Gods houſe,<note place="margin">Prov. 6.4.</note> 
                     <hi>give not ſleepe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thine eyes, nor ſlumber unto thine eye-lids;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Chro. 23.6.</note> Here muſt thou <hi>keepe the watch of the Lord;</hi> yea, leſt ſleepe ſhould aſſault thee to thy prejudice, thou muſt ſet a watch againſt the ſame, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did againſt <hi>Sanballat</hi> and <hi>Tobijah.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Neh. 4.9. Pſal. 123.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Behold as the eyes of ſervants looke unto the hand of their maſters, and as the eyes of a maiden unto the hand of her mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe:</hi> So here eſpecially ſhould our eares and eyes wait upon the Lord our God. If thou <hi>ſleepeſt at Church,</hi> thou ſhalt aſſuredly find that Gods judgements <hi>ſleepe not;</hi> yea,<note place="margin">Rev. 3.3.</note> 
                     <hi>if thou ſhalt not watch, hee will come on thee as a thiefe, wee are all children of the light, and children of the day, wee are
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:184293:86"/>not of the night,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.5. Eph. 5.14.</note> 
                     <hi>nor of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, therefore let us not ſleepe as doe others; but let us watch.</hi> Sleepeſt thou? <hi>Oh! awake thou that ſleepeſt.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 145.15.</note> 
                     <hi>The eyes of all wait on the Lord;</hi> oh! let thine alſo wait on him,<note place="margin">Pro. 20.13.</note> 
                     <hi>love not ſleepe, leſt thou come to poverty;</hi> ſleepe not at Church, leſt thou be poore in grace.<note place="margin">Gen. 15.11.</note> As <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> drave away the fowles from his ſacrifice, ſo muſt thou drowſineſſe, or what elſe may bring thee to ſleepe at Church. Awake here,<note place="margin">Pro. 6.22.</note> as thou wouldſt have the <hi>Word</hi> to <hi>keepe</hi> thee, when thou <hi>ſleepeſt</hi> elſe-where. Didſt thou conſider how Satan hath intangled thee, from which thou canſt not be looſed but by the Word, thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not <hi>give ſleepe to thine eyes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 6.4, 5.</note> 
                     <hi>nor ſlumber to thine eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lids, <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>6</label> till</hi> (by hearing the Word) <hi>thou wert delivered as a Roe from the hunter, and as a bird from the hand of the fowler. Goe to the Ant thou ſluggard,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:184293:86"/>conſider her wayes and bee wiſe. The ſleepe of a labouring man is ſweet, whether hee eate little,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.12.</note> 
                     <hi>or much,</hi> but ſuch will not bee thine at Church.<note place="margin">Act. 16.14.</note> 
                     <hi>Lydia</hi> heard attentively, and profited won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully (for, <hi>hearing is the ſenſe of learning</hi>) ſo if thou wouldſt learne, thou muſt needs heare. Here eſpecially <hi>let not thine eye bee ſatisfied with ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor thine eare with hearing.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.8.</note> Yea (attention being the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner which prepareth the way to the Preacher, as the plough-ſhare cutteth up the ground, that it may receive the ſeed) doe thou carefully attend unto the Word preached, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let Satan who labours ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſtay thee from comming to Church, or comming from hearing, or hearing from mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, or marking from liking, or liking from practiſing, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile againſt thee either way.<note place="margin">Iam. 4.7. Ionah 1.5.</note> 
                     <hi>Reſiſt him and hee will flie from thee. Jonah</hi> was faſt aſleepe
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:184293:87"/>when the boat was ready to periſh; aſſuredly now there is no time for us to ſleepe, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Gods judgements han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging over our heads. The Prophet ſaid of <hi>Baal,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">King 18.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>7</note> unto <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts by way of ironie, <hi>peradventure hee ſleepeth.</hi> I would that touching us there were a <hi>peradventure,</hi> and not rather,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Turkiſh. hiſt. pag.</hi> 654. He was mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, becauſe <hi>Solyman</hi> (whilſt he was in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour) had ſworne to him, that hee would never kill him whilſt hee li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, whom now being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepe he did repute as dead, and ſo cauſed him to bee murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> that wee doe <hi>indeed</hi> ſleepe at Church; and (as <hi>Baal</hi>) doe not heare at all. <hi>Abraham</hi> the Turkiſh <hi>Baſha</hi> would not have ſo careleſly laid himſelfe downe to ſlumber, if hee had knowne that then the angry <hi>Sultan</hi> would inflict on him the fury of his wrath to his deſtruction; and thou wouldſt not at Church, if thou didſt conceive that the Lord would then cut thee off by his deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing angell. What meanes doth not the Lord uſe to awake us; mercies, judgements, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and what not? Oh that ſome of them, or all of them
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:184293:87"/>would awake us throughly! Thou haſt heretofore ſlept at Church, but haply (as <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> forgot be like,<note place="margin">Iudg. 16.19.</note> that the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtins</hi> had once and againe bound him, whilſt hee was aſleepe, and ſo ſtill ventured on <hi>Dalilah</hi> to his deſtruction) thou haſt not taken notice of the hurt which hath come through the ſame. Hadſt thou remembred it, thou wouldſt bee more vigilant, whereunto alſo, if thou wouldſt conſider thine heavy conſtitution and drowſie diſpoſition, thou couldſt not but be ſtirred up. The <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> ſaid of <hi>Lazarus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 11.12.</note> 
                     <hi>If hee ſleepe, hee ſhall doe well.</hi> But contrarily, if thou ſleepeſt at Church, thou ſhalt doe ill. Chriſt would awake thee, Chriſt calleth upon thee, doe thou therefore awake and heare, leſt as unto his Diſciples, hee ſay unto thee in juſtice, <hi>Sleepe on now.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.16.</note> 
                     <hi>There is that neither day nor night ſeeth
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:184293:88"/>ſleepe with his eyes,</hi> ſaith the Preacher; So let it, ſo may it bee ſaid of thee, whilſt thou art at Church,<note place="margin">Mar. 14.38.</note> 
                     <hi>The Spirit truly is ready, but the fleſh is weake, watch yee therefore and pray, leſt yee enter into temptation;</hi> And what I ſay unto you,<note place="margin">Mar. 13.37.</note> I ſay unto all, in one word of our Saviour; <hi>Watch.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184293:89"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184293:89" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
